Preface

In 1975, at the instance of the Hon. Mr Justice Kutlu Fuad, the then Director of the Legal Division of the Commonwealth Secretariat, the four Directors of the Commonwealth Secretariat Legislative Drafting Scheme at the time contributed to a Legislative Drafting Manual as part of the measures undertaken at the request of Commonwealth member countries to help overcome the shortage of experienced legislative counsel. The original Manual was published in 1976 and further revised in 1978.

At their meeting in Edinburgh in 2008, Commonwealth Law Ministers examined the continuing challenges faced by small Commonwealth countries and acknowledged that it was not enough to focus solely on training legislative drafters. They recognised that different strategies in areas such as institutional strengthening, recruitment and retention of drafters, and capacity building were required. To that end, they welcomed the development of legislative drafting and style manuals and guidelines on the legislative process.

In 2013, the Hon. Justice V.C.R.A.C. Crabbe was assigned the task of producing a manual on legislative drafting, by revising the text of the original Manual. At their meeting in 2014, Commonwealth Law Ministers welcomed the production of this Manual as a valuable resource in legislative drafting across the Commonwealth and as a guide in encouraging member countries to devise their own local legislative drafting manuals, guidelines or handbooks. Ministers endorsed the proposal for the Manual to be a pan-Commonwealth legislative drafting manual and mandated the Secretariat to finalise the draft.

The present publication was extensively rewritten and updated in 2016 and 2017 by Mr Roger Rose, to reflect contemporary style and practice across the Commonwealth. The draft Manual was sent to Offices of Attorneys General in all Commonwealth member countries for review and comment, and has been enriched by input and expertise from across the Commonwealth.

The Commonwealth Legislative Drafting Manual is intended to be used as a practical tool to assist legislative counsel, in particular those in the early stages of their careers. Although hands-on practice and experience are critical for the development of skilled legislative drafters, a reference guide that sets out common drafting approaches offers a ‘go-to’ source for drafters requiring an overview of the craft, as well as suggested solutions to frequently encountered challenges. In this respect, the Manual is also a key resource for the design and delivery of legislative drafting training programmes.

As a Commonwealth product largely in the common law tradition, it is hoped that the Manual will stimulate further the interest of drafters in practising their skill, as well as providing a sense of the shared heritage in legislative drafting across the Commonwealth. The Manual provides general guidance, and must be read in each jurisdiction in the context of its own Constitution and law, and to some extent its own house style. It is intended to supplement existing textbooks and local and regional manuals. Some checklists are provided, but for more comprehensive ones reference to a standard textbook such as Thornton’s Legislative Drafting is recommended.

Some general conventions are followed in the Manual:

The expression ‘legislative counsel’ is used to refer to those who have the general task of drafting, although the term ‘drafter’ is occasionally used in relation to specific aspects of the skill, in recognition of the fact that others might also need from time to time to practise it.
Although reference is made mainly to primary legislation, except where otherwise indicated the same principles apply to the drafting of subsidiary legislation.
As the term ‘subsidiary legislation’ is more commonly used in the Commonwealth generally, it is used throughout rather than alternatives such as ‘statutory instruments’.
Although technically legislative counsel are drafting Bills and hence ‘clauses’, reference is made throughout, in most instances, to Acts, sections and subsections.
Gender-neutral drafting is adopted in both the text and illustrations (unless the illustration is from old legislation). This style is further explained in Chapter 10.

Following modern Commonwealth drafting practice, except where an old provision is used or a draft is inserted to illustrate a point, if examples are given:

the auxiliary ‘must’ is used to indicate the creation of an obligation, rather than the traditional ‘shall’ (the rationale for this is explained in Chapter 5); and
provisos are dispensed with (explained in Chapter 7).

The Manual contains 20 chapters, which address all aspects of legislative drafting, from basic drafting elements and conventions to guidance on particular legislative forms, such as preliminary, final, and penal provisions, as well as specific legislation types, such as licensing and financial legislation. The Manual further places the legislative drafting process in context, through the inclusion of appendices on the preparation of Cabinet submissions, the formulation of drafting instructions and suggested approaches to the translation of policy.

As the Manual is a living document, providing guidance in an ever-developing field, readers are warmly invited to contact the Commonwealth Secretariat with suggestions for corrections, amendments or updates accordingly.

Foreword

The global Sustainable Development Goals agreed in 2015 boldly proclaim that the development aspirations of all people everywhere are intimately linked with promotion of the rule of law.

The laws of a country touch on almost all aspects of economic, social and environmental development; they regulate economic transactions and contracts, provide for legal identity, gender equality and access to justice, as well as protect natural resources, such as water, minerals and forests.

The rule of law, as a principle of governance, requires that all laws must promote equality, accountability, and fairness. In this regard, the process by which laws are made is determinative of their ultimate quality. National legislation must be made through transparent procedures, and be drafted so as to ensure legal certainty.

Good laws therefore depend on the abilities and capabilities of legislative drafters, who are called upon to translate policy into simple, concise and lucid Bills. Bills which have clarity as their essence make the work of Parliament easier and more effective.

Legislation passed by Parliament that is clear, comprehensive, concise, and consistent, in turn, aids the work of the judiciary and public servants. It enables private enterprises and individuals to know and understand the law. It ultimately contributes to realisation of the rule of law and the promotion of sustainable development.

For many small Commonwealth jurisdictions, legislative drafting presents a significant challenge. A small jurisdiction, with perhaps just one or two parliamentary counsel, has to produce laws across the whole range of subject matter that any larger jurisdiction would also deal with. International legal obligations and regional harmonisation initiatives, as well as the pace of developments in technology, financial services, and the sciences, have further increased the need for new and amended legislation in recent years.

The Commonwealth Secretariat has, for many years, been at the forefront of providing assistance to countries in the drafting of good laws. The placement of expert advisers through the support of the Commonwealth Fund for Technical Cooperation has assisted numerous small and developing Commonwealth countries in strengthening their legislative drafting capacity.

I warmly welcome this Commonwealth Legislative Drafting Manual as a landmark tool for promoting the rule of law and development. Drawing on our shared heritage of the common law, the Manual brings together an abundance of Commonwealth experience in legislative drafting.

Alongside national drafting standards and guidelines, the Manual can act as a key knowledge tool for every Commonwealth legislative drafter. I commend its use to legislative drafting offices across the Commonwealth and salute the dedication of all involved in the preparation and promulgation of our laws. Together, I am confident that we will realise the full potential of legislation and the rule of law to contribute to our common growth and development.

The Rt Hon Patricia Scotland QC
Secretary-General of the Commonwealth

7313

7313.pdf 8 2026-03-13T06:35:16.501403 1

Chapter 5 Modern Commonwealth Conventions in Legislative Drafting

5.1 The need for consistency and conciseness

As has already been noted in Chapter 2 (‘judicial approaches’ in section 2.4), it is an important rule of drafting legislative rules that the same words and expressions are used to mean the same things, as there is a presumption that the use of a different word or expression within the same item of legislation is intentional and indicates a shift in meaning. As has already been noted (see section on ‘consistency’, Chapter 2.3) the potential for unthinking use of different words to indicate permission cannot be overemphasised:

“allow”, “authorise”, “permit”, “license”, “consent”, “let”, “sanction”, “recognise”.

But there are other important areas where there are a range of possible words meaning the same or similar things. These can most conveniently be examined by looking in turn at the most common elements of legislative sentences:

Who is affected by the rule?
What are they required to do or refrain from doing, or permitted to do?

There is also a third very common element (‘what is the consequence of failing to comply with the rule?’), but this relates to the drafting of penal provisions and will be considered in Chapter 14.

5.2 Who is affected by the rule?

A legislative rule usually states that those to whom the rule applies are required to do, or refrain from doing, something or (particularly in the case of administrators or enforcers) have a power or discretion to do or not to do something. As has already been seen (Chapter 4.1), when drafting the requisite rules, the first thing legislative counsel needs to do is to refer to the persons affected.

Bearing in mind that legislation is conventionally drafted in the third person, there are in English a number of possible ways of doing this. If it is necessary to refer to persons generally, any of the following could be written:

“anyone…”, “anybody…”, “everybody…”, “people…”, “persons…”, “any person…”, “every person…”, “a person…”

or even the old-fashioned forms ‘whoever’ or ‘whosoever’.

Depending on the shape of the sentence to be drafted, most of these can easily be expressed as negatives: ‘no-one…’, ‘no person…’, etc. However, for the sake of consistency it is necessary to choose a particular form and stick to it, and because it best represents plain language and avoids unnecessary use of words of emphasis, modern drafting convention in the Commonwealth when referring to persons generally is to use the form ‘a person’.

Note that the ordinary indefinite article ‘a’ is used, rather than a more emphatic word such as ‘any’. As will be seen in Chapter 10, the use of emphatic words ‘any’, ‘each’, ‘all’ and ‘every’ needs to be reserved for where a contrast needs to be drawn.

For drafting convenience, the meaning of ‘person’ is normally extended in an Interpretation Act or equivalent to include not only a natural person but also a body of persons, whether incorporated or unincorporated. In addition, as discussed in Chapter 4, it is often convenient to refer directly to the kind of person affected (for example a police officer, a driver, an investigator).

5.3 What is required or permitted?

When referring to what is required, forbidden or permitted, there are also numerous possible drafting alternatives available:

Imposing an obligation to do something

A person has a responsibility to…/has a duty to…/is compelled to…/is required to…/is obliged/obligated to…/is bound to…/has to…/shall…/must…

Imposing an obligation to refrain from doing something

A person is not allowed to…/is required not to…/is not permitted to…/is compelled not to…/is forbidden from…/is constrained not to…/shall not…/must not…/may not…/cannot…

Giving a discretion to do something

A person is allowed to…/is permitted to…/is entitled to…/is authorised to…/is empowered to…/has a discretion to…/may…/is able to…/can…

This can also be done by using a slightly different form relating to permitted or forbidden conduct that was often favoured in the past and is still sometimes seen:

It shall be lawful/unlawful/shall not be lawful/for a person to…

It shall be an offence for a person to…

Again, the need for consistency, as well as conciseness, has led to conventional uses of the shortest of these forms to the exclusion of the others. Traditionally ‘shall’ (and ‘shall not’) have been used to indicate obligation and ‘may’ to indicate discretion. These are known as verb auxiliaries, or merely ‘auxiliaries’. However, for reasons stated below, the conventional uses in modern Commonwealth drafting are:

A person must/must not/may/may not…

5.3.1 Problems with ‘shall’, and suggested alternatives

Indicating an obligation

The first problem is that, even in formal writing, the use of the auxiliary ‘shall’ to indicate obligation is slightly archaic. A century or more ago it was common when doing so, either in speech or writing, to state:

You shall proceed as directed.

He shall do as he is told.

In modern English these statements sound slightly awkward. Today ‘will’ tends to be substituted in each case, and indeed in conversational usage the two words have become, to an extent, interchangeable:

You will proceed as directed

He will do as he is told.

In view of the interchangeability of these auxiliaries, there is in both pairs of statements a potential problem of understanding. Do they indicate obligations or are they merely explaining what is going to happen (i.e. the future tense ^1 )? Often, particularly in spoken English, the intended meaning will be clear from the context. Nevertheless, if it is intended to indicate obligation, whether in spoken or written, formal or informal, English, the auxiliary ‘must’ is usually used. As is noted in Chapter 6, the language used in legislation needs to conform as far as possible to that in ordinary use. So in drafting a legislative rule roughly corresponding to the above statements the following would be modern conventional drafting:

A person involved in a road traffic accident must follow the instructions of a police officer called to the scene.

A driver of a heavy goods vehicle must proceed through a weighbridge as directed by…

^1 For an example of where the future tense is used to explain what is expected to happen, see the typical procedure for legislation set out in Appendix A.

Indicating a consequence or explanation

Often when the auxiliary ‘shall’ has been used in the past, it has not in fact imposed an obligation:

If an application complies with section 3, subsection (1) of this section shall not apply.

A person who contravenes this section shall be guilty of an offence.

In relation to a citizen by naturalisation, section 5 shall have effect as if the reference…

Subsection (3) shall not apply where the court gives leave to make a further application, but such leave shall not be given unless…

Except in the words following ‘but’ in the last example, each of these rules is merely stating a consequence or giving an explanation, i.e., a state of affairs brought about by, or consequence flowing from, the rule.

In the last example, the negative auxiliary ‘shall not’ is clearly used in two different senses in the same sentence (something counsel should avoid in order to preserve consistency). The intention in the second part of the sentence is to state what the duties of the court are in the relevant circumstances.

Use of the present tense to indicate states of affairs or consequences

The modern convention when expressing a state of affairs or consequence is to use the present tense . Besides being better style, this neatly gives effect to the maxim of construction ‘a statute is always speaking’ . Thus, in modern drafting, the following would take the place of the above examples:

If the application complies with section 3, subsection (1) of this section does not apply.

A person who contravenes this section is guilty of [or, probably better, commits] an offence.

In relation to a citizen by naturalisation, section 5 has effect as if the reference…

Subsection (3) does not apply where the court gives leave to make a further application, but…

A simple test to determine the way in which ‘shall’ is used is to ask whether ‘must’ can meaningfully be inserted in its place. If so, then the modern convention is to do so; if not, then the present tense or some other mode of expression is needed.

Setting out functions and duties

There are further potential problems with the overworked ‘shall’. In many cases, it is desired to set out what somebody, usually a Minister, a court or a specified official or body, is required to do. More often than not, the thrust of the provision is not so much to create an obligation or series of obligations (for the operation of the legislation concerned is usually predicated on the doing of the relevant things), but simply to state or list the powers or duties of the person concerned:

The National Heritage Trust shall:

…;
…

The objects of the Law Society shall be:

to…;
to…

The Minister shall appoint the Chairman of the Board

or, referring back to one of the original examples noted under the previous heading:

Subsection (3) does not apply where the court gives leave to make a further application, but leave [to make a further application] shall not be given unless…

Use of the present tense to indicate lists of functions or duties

In these kinds of cases, it usually better expresses the sense of the provision to use the present tense in the form ‘is to’, or ‘are to’:

The duties of the National Heritage Trust are:

to…;
to…

The objects of the Law Society are:

to…;
to…

The Minister is to appoint the Chairman of the Board

…but leave [to make a further application] is not to be given unless…

Establishing an office, corporation or other thing

The overworked ‘shall’ has been used here too:

There shall be a Registrar of Antiquities.

The Harbours Authority shall be a body corporate with perpetual succession and a common seal…

A tax, to be known as “land transaction tax”, shall be charged and collected…

In these cases, as with those examined in the paragraph above on use of the present tense, the troublesome auxiliary is better replaced by ‘is to’ or, in the second example, by replacing ‘shall be’ with ‘is’.

Explaining provisions

Recourse has also sometimes been made to ‘shall’ for an explanatory purpose:

An interim order shall not be deemed to be an adoption order within the meaning of this Act.

The Board shall be lawfully constituted if there are no less than 7 elected members present.

In fact ‘be deemed to be’ in the first example is a slightly archaic form hardly ever used even in formal language outside legislation (in modern writing, the equivalent would be ‘be treated as’, ‘be regarded as’ or ‘be taken to be’), and so applying the conventions already discussed, one would write:

An interim order is not to be regarded as an adoption order within the meaning of this Act.

although, applying principles of conciseness, use in this context of the words ‘deemed to be’ is arguably redundant, and the better draft would be:

An interim order is not an adoption order within the meaning of this Act.

In the second example, all that is needed is ‘…is lawfully constituted if…’

5.3.2 Potential problems with ‘may’

The use of ‘can’

As has been seen, from the variety of words and expressions that could be used to indicate discretion, ‘may’ is the one usually chosen. Of course in informal spoken language another verb auxiliary ‘can’ is often used in the same sense:

You can call me by my first name or my nickname.

He can do whatever he thinks is right in the circumstances.

In formal English, however, it is not correct to do this. ‘Can’ in its correct use is synonymous with ‘is able to’ and should be reserved for referring to physical or mental ability to do something, rather than having permission to do it. What is needed is a word indicating permission or discretion. Legislative equivalents of the above examples might be:

An Act may be referred to by its short title or chapter number.

The Authority may direct a course of action that it considers appropriate in the circumstances.

The use of ‘may not’

At first sight the negative form ‘may not’ seems to have the same meaning as the negative obligation form ‘must not’, and indeed in spoken language any of the following might be stated interchangeably:

You must not smoke in here.

You may not smoke in here.

or even:

You cannot smoke in here.

The third version has already been considered, but there is also a fine but important distinction between the first two. In legislative rules, ‘must not’ is used to create an obligation not to do something; ‘may not’, on the other hand, is reserved for cases in which it is required to emphasise a lack of authority to do something (without necessarily incurring a penalty for contravention):

A licensee may not apply to renew a licence more than 30 days before it is due to expire.

A court may not convict a person of an offence under this section if that person has paid the relevant fixed penalty.

In these cases, the sense is not so much to forbid a person from doing something as to indicate or explain the lack of a right or discretion. A licensee who failed to comply would presumably simply be told to reapply at the correct time and, in the unlikely event that a person were actually to be convicted of the specified offence in the circumstances mentioned, he or she would have an unanswerable appeal.

Contrast, however, the more usual type of case:

A person must not carry on the business of a hawker unless he or she holds a hawker’s licence of the appropriate class.

This clearly creates an important negative obligation, and there would undoubtedly have to be a provision following it making anybody who failed to comply liable to penal sanctions.

Other meanings of ‘may’

Finally, there is sometimes inconsistent use of ‘may’ in the sense of ‘is’ (or ‘are’) and ‘might’:

In sections 3 to 9 of this Act a reference to adoption is to adoption of an infant wherever the infant may be habitually resident.

Although there would not in practice be any difficulty in understanding this provision, it would be better from the point of view of consistency to use ‘is’ instead of ‘may be’.

Furthermore, an ambiguity could possibly arise with inconsistent use, particularly if the auxiliary is capable of meaning ‘might’:

The Minister may not make an order if the circumstances set out in subsection (3) apply.

The application of this Act may be subject to such modifications as are prescribed.

The first could be construed either as a lack of power in the specified circumstances or (if ‘may’ is understood in the sense of ‘might’) as an explanation of the way in which that power could be expected to be exercised in a particular case. In addition, the question arises with regard to the second example as to whether the sentence confers a power to make modifications or (as in the first example) is an explanation of what might happen. Although legislation is construed as creating rules rather than giving explanations, it would nevertheless be better to redraft the above provisions:

The Minister [is not to] [must not] make an order if the circumstances set out in subsection (3) apply.

The application of this Act is subject to such modifications as are prescribed.

7314

7314.pdf 8 2026-03-13T06:36:50.993822 1

Chapter 6 Plain Language Drafting

6.1 Introduction

The general Commonwealth trend has been to move away from the traditional drafting styles of the past involving the use of largely unfamiliar words and expressions and lengthy sentences, which were thought to be necessary in the interests of conveying precise meaning.

Recent changes in perception have recognised that legal writing generally, and legislation in particular, should be able as far as possible to be readily understood by those to be affected by it. It has come to be seen as a waste of resources for legal documents to have to be ‘translated’ into everyday language by lawyers. It has also come to be recognised that the former styles (sometimes mockingly known as ‘legalese’) can take on a life of their own, so that drafters using them can fall into patterns of both thought and writing that may cause a failure to adequately address the drafting problems.

There are still many people who remain unconvinced by some of these changes (including the move away from the auxiliary ‘shall’, discussed in Chapter 5), especially in more conservative jurisdictions and especially among some MPs and members of the legal profession. It may thus not be a matter of individuals (unless in very senior positions) being able to take it upon themselves to change things in the ways proposed. The introduction of new drafting practices is thus an issue that may require tact and perseverance.

6.2 Reasons why legislation may fail to communicate clearly

The most obvious of these is that legislative provisions are imprecise or difficult to understand because the thinking behind them is unclear:

(2) A person shall be deemed to deposit or dump waste under this Act if he deposits or dumps the waste, whether solid, semi-solid or liquid, in such circumstances, or for such period that he may be deemed:

(a) to have abandoned it where it is deposited or dumped; or

(b) to have brought it to the place where it is so deposited or dumped for the purpose of its being disposed of or abandoned whether by him or any other person.

See further the examples in section 6.4 relating to the passive voice and modifiers.

However, even though the thinking behind them is probably clear and the language attempts to be precise, they may still for various reasons be difficult to read and understand (see the other examples in section 6.4).

6.3 General objective of plain English in drafting legislation

To communicate more effectively with those to whom a document is addressed, and in doing so to:

use language that is simple, direct, economical and familiar
omit unnecessary or repetitious words or phrases
use sentence structures that avoid ambiguity or undue complexity
organise and present sentences in a way that enables their meaning to be grasped as quickly as possible.

6.4 The most common specific problems that need to be addressed

6.4.1 Excessively long sentences

Sentences that exceed 20 to 30 words present problems of understanding unless the text is broken up (see Chapter 7).

No action, suit, prosecution or other proceeding whatsoever shall lie or be brought, instituted or maintained in any court or before any other authority against the Government, a State Government, the Central Bank, any officer or employee of any such Government or of the Central Bank, either personally or in his official capacity, or any person lawfully acting on behalf of any such Government or the Central Bank, or on behalf of any such officer or employee, either personally or in his capacity as a person acting on such behalf, for or on account of, or in respect of, any act done or statement made, or omitted to be done or made, or purporting to be done or made or omitted to be done or made, in pursuance or in execution of, or intended pursuance of, this Act, or any order in writing, direction, instruction, notice or other thing whatsoever issued under this Act.

Difficulty in reading and understanding this sentence arises because it is not concise and contains too many detailed and confusing references to persons and complex context conditions.

6.4.2 Legislative sentences do not follow standard English usage

Complex verb constructions or inconsistencies with modern grammatical practice make for difficulty in understanding, for example, different uses of the auxiliary ‘shall’ (see further Chapter 5); use of deeming provisions; and use of provisos:

A person who shall have received a fee for advising another person in relation to an investment shall be deemed to have advised that person in the course of business:

Provided that he shall not be deemed to have done so in the course of business if he shall prove that…

Rather state:

A person who receives a fee for advising another person about an investment is to be regarded as having done so in the course of business, unless the person advising proves that…

The word ‘deem’ in provisions that create a legal fiction or (as here) a rule of interpretation is slightly archaic and needs to be replaced by a modern equivalent such as that used in the example above (or others such as ‘be treated as’). Discouragement of the use of provisos will be considered further in Chapter 7 (‘Structuring legislative drafts’, section on grouping provisions). Note also that the redrafted version is in gender-neutral language (see further Chapter 10).

6.4.3 Use of archaic or pretentious words and expressions

Avoid meaningless or cumbersome words and expressions of reference or stress such as ‘aforesaid’, ‘hereby’, ‘hereinbefore mentioned’ and ‘whatsoever’. See further examples in the list at the end of this chapter.

Elements of the following hypothetical, and, by modern standards, slightly preposterous archaic writing, can still sometimes be seen:

15. (1) Whosoever ^1 shall be ^2 seised of ^3 chattels real ^4 to which the immediately preceding section of this Act ^5 relates ^6 , shall not ^7 utilise ^8 the said chattels ^9 for the purposes of ^10 hire, reward ^11 or sale before the expiration of ^12 the hereinafter in this section mentioned ^13 relevant period of time.

Modern use would be ‘A person (who)…’.
This is the future tense. The present tense should be used.
Archaic word for ‘possess’ in relation to leasehold property.
Archaic word for interests in land less than freehold (it usually refers to leaseholds).
A pretentious (and potentially confusing) reference, which should be to the relevant section number, and there is normally no need to use ‘of this Act’.
‘Refer’ is a more modern word.
‘Must’ and ‘must not’ are the auxiliaries in everyday use indicating obligation.
A pretentious form of ‘use’. Even that word can be avoided here.
‘The said’ is an archaic and unnecessary expression of reference.
‘For the purposes of’ means no more than ‘for’.
‘Hire or reward’ is a stock lawyer’s phrase. Consideration should be given to more apt or precise terms if possible.
A pretentious (and often used) alternative to ‘expiry of’ or ‘end of’.
Pretentious, clumsy and archaic style. In this context, it is apparent that the specification will be made later in section 15.

Rather, the proposition ought to be stated thus:

15. (1) A person in possession of leasehold premises referred to in section 14 must not offer them for subletting, mortgage or sale until the specified time period has ended.

6.4.4 Careless use of the passive voice

The potential danger caused by this has already been noted in Chapter 4 (section 4.1 on ‘Legal subject’). It is not suggested that this form of expression should be avoided altogether, but unthinking use can cause problems of understanding. The following example is from a Narcotic Drugs Act:

27. Where a medical practitioner is convicted of an offence under this Act, he shall be liable to have his name removed from the register of those licensed or registered to practice as a medical practitioner.

Here the drafter has not addressed his or her mind to who is to do the removing. Is it the registrar (no mention of whom is made in this particular Act), or is it the court? See further Chapter 14 (‘Penal provisions’).

On the other hand, the use of the passive would be convenient in the following example:

If a vessel is wrecked, stranded or in distress on or near the coast, any cargo or other article belonging to or separated from the vessel which is washed on shore or otherwise lost or taken from the vessel must be delivered to the receiver.

Here it is perfectly clear who is addressed by the rule (i.e. anyone finding cargo, etc., from a wreck, etc.) and to draft in the active voice would require many more words (58 as against 45):

If a vessel is wrecked, stranded or in distress on or near the coast, a person who comes into possession of the cargo or any part of it, or any other article belonging to or separated from the vessel which is washed on shore or otherwise lost or taken from the vessel must deliver it to the receiver.

6.4.5 Careless use of dangling modifiers

A potential danger in drafting legislation is that modifiers (adjectival and adverbial words, phrases and clauses) are left ‘dangling’, so that it is unclear to which word or set of words they attach. Extreme care needs to be taken to ensure that this does not happen:

The Board may make annual grants to persons from its general fund or from any of its other funds with the approval of the Minister.

The underlined adverbial phrase dangles because it is possible to read the underlined words either as modifying only grants from ‘other funds’ or as modifying ‘general fund’ as well. This can be clarified by correct use of punctuation, or by changing the word order, or both. Thus:

The Board may make annual grants to persons from its general fund or, with the approval of the Minister, from any of its other funds.

or, depending on the policy:

The Board may, with the approval of the Minister, make annual grants to persons from its general fund or from any of its other funds.

Where a dangling modifier appears in the middle of a sentence and is capable of applying equally to words or groups of words which precede or follow, it is said to ‘squint’. Thus:

The Commissioner may order an importer within seven days of importation of the goods to file an affidavit stating…

It is not clear whether the underlined adverbial phrase modifies ‘may order’ or ‘file an affidavit’. Again, the ambiguity is avoided by punctuating correctly and placing the underlined phrase in the correct position in the sentence:

The Commissioner may, within seven days of importation of the goods, order an importer to file an affidavit stating…

or, depending on the policy:

The Commissioner may order an importer to file, within seven days of importation of goods, an affidavit stating…

6.4.6 Excessive use of cross-referencing

Reliance on other provisions, in the same or other legislation, while it has a limited place in legislation, often calls for searching in other pieces of legislation that may not be available to the user, and sometimes (e.g. where mutatis mutandis or a similar expression is used) for statutory construction of the other provisions.

Subject to the provisions of the Evidence Act, and to any rules made under section 356(1)(f) of this Act, the record of a confession made in accordance with this section is admissible in evidence against the person who made it.

In this Act "bank" has the meaning given in Part II of the Banking Act, and "financial institution" has the meaning given by section 3 of the Financial Institutions Act.

"interest in a share" is to be construed as provided under section 225(2) to (10) of the Companies Act, read with the following modifications:

(a) the substitution of "including" for "otherwise than" in subsection (6)(d); and

(b) the deletion of subsection (9)(b).

6.5 The aims of plain English in legislation

To limit the ideas expressed in a legislative sentence
Not to allow sentences to get too long so as to interfere with communication of the central message of the provision
Where necessary, to break up the format of sentences into paragraphs (see Chapter 7)
To follow the standard usage and styles of modern English
To use words in common use rather than elaborate or obscure ones (see the lists below)
To eliminate unnecessary words and expressions
To avoid cumbersome and unnecessary words of reference or emphasis
To avoid archaic words and expressions
To avoid Latin and French words or expressions as far as possible (see the lists below)
To use the active rather than the passive form as a general rule
To avoid dangling modifiers
As far as possible, to limit the use of cross-referencing to other parts of the legislation and, even more so, to other legislation.

6.6 Words and phrases to avoid or use with care

Archaic words to avoid or replace

aforesaid, said : the, that
hereby : [omit]
hereinafter/before : in section(s)… etc.
lessee : tenant
lessor : landlord
provided that : but, however
servant : employee
such (pronoun: ‘if such was the case’): it, that, they
thereafter (-in, -under, etc.): after (in, under) it
thereupon : then
the same (pronoun: ‘if the same has been declared unfit…’): it, they

Words and phrases to avoid or use sparingly

as a consequence of : because of
by means of : by
by virtue of : by, under
despite the fact that : although
endeavour : try
expiration of : end of, expiry of
for the purpose of : to
in accordance with : as, under
in pursuance of : as, under
in relation to : about, concerning
in the event that : if
notwithstanding : despite
prior to : before
purchase : buy
subsequent to : after
such (adjective: ‘such persons who…’): the, that, those
until such time as : until
with a view to : to
with reference to : about, concerning
with regard to : about, concerning
with respect to : on, about

Pairs of words meaning the same thing

due and payable : due, payable
fit and proper : fit, suitable
just and equitable : just, equitable, reasonable, fair
null and void : void, of no effect
save and except : except, unless
unless and until : unless, until

Latin phrases to avoid or use sparingly

ab initio : from the outset, …beginning
ad valorem : related to the value
bona fide : in good faith
de facto/jure : in fact/law
de novo : again, re-…
doli incapax : incapable of (committing) crime
ex parte : without notice to the other party
in camera : in closed court
in extremis : on the point of death
in loco parentis : in place of a parent
in pari materia : analogous with
inter alia : among(st) other things
inter alios : among(st) other persons
mutatis mutandis : with the necessary changes
per se : in itself
pro rata : proportionately
sine die : with no fixed date, indefinitely
sui generis : of its own kind, in its own category
sui juris : under no legal disability

But note that the following Latin expressions have gained common acceptance as technical legal ones that do not easily translate into a convenient plain English equivalent

certiorari : [to be more carefully informed]
ex gratia : as a matter of favour, without legal obligation
ex officio : by virtue of appointment/post/office
habeas corpus : [you have the body]
intra/ultra vires : [within/beyond the powers]
mandamus : [we command]
mens rea : [guilty mind]
nolle prosequi : [unwilling to prosecute]
post mortem : [after death]
prima facie : [at first glance]
pro forma : [for form’s sake]

7315

7315.pdf 8 2026-03-13T06:38:39.460187 1

Chapter 7 Structuring Legislative Drafts

7.1 Sentences

Each distinct legal proposition should be comprised in a single sentence. In legislative terms this means a section or subsection. If a legal proposition is contained in more than one subsection, each should have a close enough relationship to provide a unity of purpose. The following example would not comply with this convention:

Appointment and duties of film censors
5. (1) The Minister may appoint as many film censors as the Minister considers necessary.
(2) The film censors are to perform the duties assigned to them in accordance with general directions given to them by the Minister.
(3) No film is to be shown unless there is in force in respect of it a certificate of censorship granted by a film censor under section 8.

As can quickly be seen, subsection (3) introduces a quite different subject matter.

The length of a sentence needs to be dictated by the following considerations:

readers cannot normally digest more than 4 to 5 lines of unbroken text without re-reading (see the first example in section 6.4); and
sentences over that size need to be broken into paragraphs.

On the other hand:

several short sentences (of less than 2 lines) may be difficult to relate together; and
extensive linking may get in the way of understanding the content (see section 7.4).

7.2 Paragraphs

7.2.1 Particular uses

Tabulations, listing a series of attributes, contents, duties, etc.:

A dealer must maintain a register in which is recorded:
(a) the prescribed particulars of goods acquired;
(b) the name, address and business of the person from whom the goods are acquired; and
(c) the date and time of acquisition.

Developing an underlying theme in an orderly way (in the following case, duties of the dealer with regard to goods acquired):

A dealer who, except from another licensed dealer, acquires goods specified in the Second Schedule:
(a) must retain possession of the goods for at least 30 days;
(b) must not alter the condition or appearance of the goods during that time; and
(c) in the case of precious stones removed from jewellery after 30 days and sold, must record the weight and description of each stone that is over the prescribed size.

Reducing repetition (in the following example preventing the repetition of ‘A dealer must display’):

A dealer must display:
(a) in a conspicuous place at the dealer’s premises, a copy of the licence; and
(b) at the entrance to those premises, a prescribed sign.

Reducing ambiguity (e.g. where an unstructured sentence leaves a dangling modifier – see Chapter 6):

The Minister may make grants to public or charitable:
(a) hospitals;
(b) schools; or
(c) research institutions.

Making context clauses more readable:

If:
(a) the complainant does not appear at the time and place appointed for the hearing of a charge; and
(b) the court is satisfied that the complainant had notice of that time and place,
the court must acquit the accused unless, for reasons to be recorded, it decides to adjourn the case.

However, care needs to be taken not to over-paragraph and to ensure that introducing or concluding words apply to each of the paragraphs in a sequence. Each paragraph must be able to be read as flowing grammatically from the introducing words. Likewise, any concluding words must flow grammatically from each paragraph.

In some jurisdictions it is regarded as bad style to draft concluding words after a paragraph series, so that the paragraphs become ‘sandwiched’ between other words of the sentence, but there seems no good reason to avoid this format unless it can be seen to cause possible difficulty in understanding.

7.2.2 Misuse of paragraphs

The following are common examples of misuse:

breaking the grammatical structure:

A person using the library:
(a) must not damage a book in any way, and if the person does so he or she is liable for the cost of its repair;
(b) must return a book borrowed within the specified period.

including in one paragraph words intended to apply also to some or all of the other paragraphs:

A dealer must display:
(a) in a conspicuous place at the entrance to his premises, a copy of his or her licence;
(b) a prescribed signboard.

the introductory words do not apply to each of the paragraphs that follow:

Nothing in this section authorises the Minister to delegate:
(a) a power to issue warrants;
(b) to make proclamations; or
(c) any function, the delegation of which is expressly forbidden by law.

words following the final paragraph do not apply to each of the paragraphs:

If a person:
(a) other than from a licensed dealer obtains; or
(b) other than to a licensed agent disposes;
of goods specified in the Second Schedule, that person commits an offence.

lack of a vital linking word:

A person who:
(a) comes into possession of;
(b) disposes of,
stolen goods commits an offence.

7.3 Grouping provisions in an Act

For the conventional arrangement of an Act, see Figure 7.1 at the end of this chapter. This will need to be modified or adapted according to the type of Act being drafted. For example, an amending Act would be unlikely to have most of the preliminary provisions and not all legislation will need all of the miscellaneous and final provisions.

7.3.1 Devices for grouping provisions in an Act

For convenience reference is made to ‘an Act’, but exactly the same considerations apply to subsidiary legislation:

Divisions larger than a section (the use of these devices is not standardised in Commonwealth drafting, and variations sometimes apply in different jurisdictions, and even to statutes drafted in different decades within the same jurisdiction):

Chapters: Typically found in the Constitution and very long pieces of legislation such as a Criminal Procedure Act or Companies Act;
Parts: Standard devices for referring to groups of sections dealing with the same theme;
Divisions: Used in longer legislation as sub-groupings either of Chapters or of Parts; and
Headings or sub-divisions: Sub-groupings within Parts.

When grouping provisions within an Act, legislative counsel needs to consider the length and complexity of the legislation. Clearly the longer the legislation the more likely will be the need for divisions greater than a section; there is no point in so dividing a short Act whose effect is clear.

Sections and divisions of sections (the following are conventional Commonwealth designations):

Sections [designated as 1. 2. 3. etc.] each containing a separate legal proposition;
Subsections [designated as (1), (2), (3), etc.] each having a unity of purpose with others in that section;
Paragraphs [designated (a), (b), (c), etc.] each of which constitutes an element of the proposition advanced in a section or subsection;
Subparagraphs [designated as (i), (ii), (iii), etc.] each of which constitutes an element of the proposition advanced in a paragraph; and
Sub-subparagraphs [usually designated as (A), (B), (C), etc.] a lower level still which should be needed only exceptionally.

7.3.2 Headings and section notes

In most jurisdictions these are treated as editorial rather than legislative (i.e. they do not form part of the formal text for the purposes of construction). They should be brief (a single word will often suffice) and accurate summaries of the contents of a section or group of sections. Exceptionally, the abbreviation ‘etc.’ (which should never be used in the body of the text of rules) may be used. Thus, rather than:

Duty of the Commission to keep accounts
Persons may not object to supplying information, documents or things to the Commission

It would be better to draft, respectively:

Accounts
Supply of information, etc.

7.4 Linking devices

7.4.1 Linking within a sentence

This is to indicate a connection with persons or things already referred to:

If a person has instituted proceedings under this Act, nothing in this section prevents the withdrawing of those (note, not “such”) proceedings by or at the instance of that person .

In some jurisdictions ‘the’ would be substituted for each of the underlined words.

7.4.2 Linking between one sentence (i.e. section or subsection) and another

Often the relationship indicated by the linking expression is clear and direct:

Section 6 does not apply to the proprietor of a newspaper who has a policy of insurance in respect of damages that may be awarded…
The persons referred to in subsection (1) are not eligible for re-election if…
A function of the Board set out in section 4…
A licence granted under this Part…

However, confusion sometimes exists between two very common expressions that indicate a relationship between sentences:

‘subject to’ and
‘notwithstanding’ (or its more modern equivalent ‘despite’).

The difference between them needs to be clearly understood:

5. Subject to section 4, the Authority may grant a licence to a person who…

This indicates that the provision referred to is the dominant one, i.e., to some extent section 4 overrides section 5. In practice, this usually means that section 5 constitutes an explanation, extension or refinement of the rule in section 4.

On the other hand:

5. Despite section 4, the Authority may not grant a licence to a person who…

indicates that the provision in which this expression appears (i.e. section 5) is the dominant one. This usually means that it constitutes an exception to, or exemption from, the provision referred to.

7.4.3 Provisos

A device, much used in the past, has been the creation of a proviso or provisos (‘provided that…’ or the even more cumbersome ‘provided always that…’) to a section or subsection.

The device has been used mainly for cases where an exception or qualification to a general proposition is to be created. However, it is often used in other senses, for example to explain or elaborate on a proposition:

A legal practitioner must pay an annual fee according to the scale set out in the Schedule:
Provided that this section does not apply to a practitioner who is not in actual practice.

Neither the Corporation nor an officer of the Corporation is liable for damages on account of an act done or statement made under this Act:
Provided that the act or statement was done or made in good faith.

Because of its slightly archaic structure (provisos are rarely if ever used outside legislation or legal documents generally), and its inconsistent usage, the use of this device is discouraged. Alternatives to provisos can always be created by using words or expressions such as ‘but’, ‘however’, ‘nevertheless’ or ‘except’, or by restructuring the sentence. The two examples above would be better written:

A legal practitioner must pay an annual fee according to the scale set out in the Schedule; [but] [however] this section does not apply to a practitioner who is not in actual practice.

or

A legal practitioner other than one who is not in actual practice must pay an annual fee…

Neither the Corporation nor an officer of the Corporation is liable for damages on account of an act done or statement made in good faith under this Act:

Where inclusion of the required information would make the sentence too long or complex, then the information should be drafted as a new sentence (usually a further subsection or the equivalent in subsidiary legislation).

Only those provisions marked with an asterisk will be required as standard ones in any Bill.

In some jurisdictions (e.g. the UK, Nigeria and South Africa), some or all of the above preliminary provisions (short title, commencement and interpretation) are placed with the final provisions.

This arrangement also applies, from preliminary provisions on, to major subsidiary legislation (i.e. Regulations and Rules so called; see Chapter 15), except that there the short title is usually known as the ‘citation’.

Figure 7.1 Conventional Commonwealth Arrangement of a Bill

Introductory provisions

Long title*
Preamble
Commencement date*
Enacting formula*

Preliminary provisions

Short title*
Commencement
Interpretation
Objects or purposes
Application
Duration

Principal provisions

Substantive matters*
Administrative matters

General and miscellaneous provisions

Penal
Evidence and process
Delegated powers to legislate

Final provisions

Amendments
Repeals
Transitional and savings

Schedules

Chapter 11 The Legislative Scheme: Principles Governing the Type of Legislation Required and the Ordering of Its Provisions

11.1 Fundamental questions to be answered

These are not always adequately addressed by those giving instructions to legislative counsel, and it is the latter’s responsibility to establish fundamental matters at the outset.

11.1.1 Matters relating to the type of legislation required

Can the required policy be implemented by amending existing legislation?
Is the new legislation to be self-contained or is more than one piece of legislation required?
Is it going to need amplification by subsidiary legislation, and if so how far? (see further Chapter 15).

11.1.2 Matters relating to the legal mechanisms to be employed

A clear idea is also needed as to what the fundamental nature of the legislation is, so that a basic view can be taken with regard to its shape. Is it, for example, criminal in nature, revenue collecting or administrative? Typical further basic questions would be:

Are rights and duties under the civil law to be extended or limited?
Is licensing or registration the principal purpose?
Is a new authority to be created and how central to the legislation will it be?
Is the legislation of a ‘portmanteau’ type (i.e. dealing with a wide range of sometimes unrelated matters, such as miscellaneous minor amendments)?

11.2 A logical structure to legislation

A logical structure to legislation is needed so that its meaning can be communicated as quickly and easily as possible. The need exists both at the level of a whole Act and, as will be seen in section 11.3, within each single section.

Having decided on the type of legislation required, the next questions relate to how the items for inclusion are to be arranged so that the layout is logical and facilitates communication and use. The basic conventional Commonwealth structure of an Act can be seen in Figure 7.1, but attention now needs to be focussed on what are called the substantive and administrative provisions.

Except in the case of a short enactment of less than about 12–14 sections, there needs to be a selection of criteria for dividing groups of sections into Parts (in long enactments, the same applies to groupings larger than Parts, for example Chapters, Divisions). An intelligible pattern needs to be provided so that provisions are not scattered randomly through the enactment; themes therefore need to be identified that suggest combinations of sections with an obvious connection:

in an Act setting up a new authority, these would be concerned with establishment and composition of the Authority; its functions and powers; procedures in its meetings; finance and audit requirements; appeals; and offences (see further Chapter 18)
in an Act setting up a licensing regime, they would concern where the need for a licence arises, what qualifications are needed, how it is to be applied for, the duties of a licence holder, offences, etc. (see further Chapter 19).

All the relevant sections should then be gathered into the Parts decided on.

11.3 The logical sequence of sections within a Part

This must then be worked out, using the following rules:

the general precedes the particular
the important precedes the secondary
the basic theme precedes the development of it
the standard case precedes the exceptions
the rules likely to be frequently applied precede those likely to be less frequently applied
the permanent precedes the temporary
where successive steps are to be taken, the earlier precedes the later.

Exactly the same principles apply to the grouping of subsections within a section.

A simple example of the misapplication of these rules can be seen in the following section:

Warrants in respect of undercover operations

(1) A warrant under this section must be signed by the Minister.

(2) Unless previously terminated, a warrant ceases to have effect:
(a) on completion of the undercover operation to which it relates; or
(b) at the end of six months from its date of issue,
whichever is sooner.

(3) The Minister may issue a warrant directed to the Commissioner of Police authorising the undertaking of a controlled undercover operation.

By application of the above rules, in particular the first three and the last, it can quickly be seen that the giving of the power must precede provisions on detail, and that there is a need to recognise the chronology, so that matters concerning the form of a warrant precede those relating to its termination. Thus the subsections would in practice need to be re-ordered:

(1) The Minister may issue a warrant directed to the Commissioner of Police authorising the undertaking of a controlled undercover operation.

(2) A warrant under this section must be signed by the Minister.

(3) Unless previously terminated, a warrant ceases to have effect:
(a) on completion of the undercover operation to which it relates; or
(b) at the end of six months from its date of issue,
whichever is sooner.

7322

7322.pdf 12 2026-03-13T06:50:34.738893 1

Chapter 14 Penal Provisions

14.1 General formulae

The same care must be taken to draft penal provisions as any others. Legislative counsel must be prepared to ask why a particular format has been used in the past, and whether aspects of the style used are appropriate in modern drafting. The following over-elaborate provision brings this out:

Any person who makes any false statement during the course of making an application for a licence shall be guilty of an offence and liable, on conviction by a court of competent jurisdiction, to imprisonment for a term not exceeding three months, or to a fine not exceeding five thousand dollars, or to both such fine and such imprisonment.

In most Commonwealth jurisdictions there are provisions in the Interpretation Act or Criminal Procedure Act (or equivalents) to the following effect:

Where in a written law a penalty is specified in respect of an offence, unless otherwise stated that penalty is the maximum penalty that may be imposed for that offence.

Applying this rule, as well as rules on conciseness, elliptical writing (see Chapter 10.7) and plain language principles (including the writing of figures instead of words to represent numbers) to the text at the beginning, it will quickly be apparent that this can be reduced to:

A person who makes a false statement when applying for a licence commits an offence and is liable to imprisonment for 3 months, or a fine of $5,000, or both.

There is often another important background rule in the Interpretation Act or Criminal Procedure Act:

Where in a written law more than one penalty is specified in respect of an offence, the use of the word "and" between the respective penalties means that the penalties may be imposed in the alternative or cumulatively.

By using this, the penal provision stated above can be further reduced to:

A person who makes a false statement when applying for a licence commits an offence and is liable to imprisonment for 3 months and a fine of $5,000.

Note that there are normally three elements of an offence provision:

a statement of the prohibited act or omission ('a person who…. '; 'a person must not… ');
a declaration that contravention of the prohibition is an offence ('commits an offence'); and
specification of the maximum penalty ('and is liable to……. ').

However, the second element is sometimes omitted as being implied:

A person who fails to deliver to the receiver an item recovered from a wrecked or stranded vessel is liable to imprisonment for 2 years.

The archaic or over-elaborate introductory words still seen in Penal Codes drafted a long time ago should not be used:

Whosoever shall make any false statement…shall be guilty of an offence.

It shall be unlawful for any person to make any false statement…

In this section and section 14.2 it is presumed that the stated penalties are maximum penalties. Sometimes it is desired to create fixed or minimum penalties, and these are considered under section 14.6.1 and 2.

14.2 Different types of penalties

14.2.1 First and subsequent offences

It is sometimes thought desirable to make a distinction between a first offender and a subsequent one in the penalty provided, particularly in the case of regulatory offences in which there might be strict liability (see section 14.4) and possibly a misunderstanding of the requirements of the law;

A person who advertises a tobacco product contrary to the provisions of this Act commits an offence and is liable:

for a first offence, to a fine of $20,000;
for a second or subsequent offence, to imprisonment for 6 months and a fine of $50,000.

14.2.2 Continuing offences

In certain areas of the law it is desirable not only to subject an offender to a penalty, but also to discourage the person from continuing to offend. This is especially so in legislation requiring the filing of necessary information, or the payment of money owing:

A person who fails to submit a return as provided by section 42 commits an offence and is liable to a fine of $2,500, and if the failure continues for more than 30 days after the last day for submission under that section, to a further fine of $25 for every day or part of a day during which the offence continues.

14.2.3 Serious offences

There are usually background rules (in e.g. the Criminal Procedure Act) allowing a court to sentence an offender to pay a fine or impose another non-custodial sentence as an alternative to imprisonment. If so, with offences that carry a potential sentence of imprisonment of more than 1 year, it is not necessary to provide for a maximum financial penalty. In these cases, the penalty may then be more simply expressed, for example:

A person who assaults an inspector in the execution of his or her duty under this Act commits an offence and is liable to imprisonment for 2 years.

But it might be different if, for example, it were desired to provide for a maximum fine greater than that usually considered to be a corresponding alternative (see further section 14.6):

A person who forges a licence, or falsely represents that he or she is licensed under this Act, commits an offence and is liable to imprisonment for 2 years and a fine of $5,000,000.

14.2.4 Sliding scales

These are especially useful in situations of inflation, where stated monetary penalties can quickly become absurdly small. By expressing these penalties in relation to a published scale, and giving the Minister the power to amend that scale (by subsidiary legislation) in accordance with variations in the value of money, the problem of having to amend individual penalties by statutory amendment is avoided. This is typically done in the following way:

There is established a scale of fines for offences, to be known as "the standard scale".
The standard scale is divided into 5 levels and the Minister may by order fix the maximum fine in each level.
Where an enactment, whether passed before or after the commencement of this Act:

provides that a person is liable to a fine; or
confers power by subsidiary legislation to make a person liable to a fine, by reference to a specified level on the standard scale, that enactment is to be construed as referring to the maximum fine for that level on the standard scale for the time being fixed under this section.

An example of a provision following the above rule would be:

A person who commits an offence under this section is liable to a fine at level 3 on the standard scale.

14.2.5 Related penalties

These are useful in situations where the value of items (including licences) that are the subject of legislation is easily ascertainable:

A person who fails to declare goods to Customs commits an offence and is liable to pay, in addition to the duty payable on the goods, a fine not exceeding five times the value of the goods as assessed under section 21.

14.3 Parties to offences

14.3.1 Particular offenders

Corporations

The following type of provision is used to clarify the fact that where a body of persons commits an offence, those who are responsible for running the affairs of the body also commit that offence:

Where an offence is committed by a body corporate or by a society, association or body of persons, a person who at the time of the offence was concerned with, or acting in, the management of the affairs or activities of the body corporate, society, association or body of persons also commits that offence unless he or she proves:

that the offence was committed without his or her knowledge; or
that he or she took all reasonable steps to prevent the commission of the offence.

There are possible variations of this, so that the paragraphs above might instead provide (note the different conjunction between the paragraphs):

that the offence was committed without his or her consent; and
that he or she took all reasonable steps to prevent the commission of the offence.

Secondary offenders

General criminal provisions normally cover the criminal liability of those traditionally known as aiders and abetters without the need to set this out in individual provisions:

A person who assists in the commission of an offence, or who arranges for, or advises or encourages, another person to commit an offence, also commits that offence and may be charged with having actually committed it.

14.3.2 Vicarious liability

This is generally a concept which applies in the civil rather than the criminal law, but sometimes the law does make a principal vicariously liable for an offence committed by an employee or agent, the rationale being that the former has a particularly high standard of responsibility for seeing that the legislative provisions are complied with. Areas of the criminal law in which vicarious liability has been applied are protection of the environment, safety at work, responsibility for the acts of children and of animals, and minor traffic offences:

Where a ship to which this section applies discharges oil into navigable waters, the owner as well as the master commits an offence.

Subject to subsection (2), the person who is the registered keeper of a motor vehicle in respect of which a parking offence is committed is guilty of that offence.
A registered keeper is not guilty under subsection (1) if:

a notice has been served on him or her under section 46 requiring information as to the person in charge of the vehicle, and within 7 days the keeper has:

given to the police the name and address of the person who was in charge of the vehicle at the relevant time; or
satisfied the police that he or she did not know, and could not with reasonable diligence have found out, that name and address; or

in any other case the keeper satisfies the court that he or she did not know, and could not with reasonable diligence have found out, that name and address.

14.4 Strict liability in criminal law

There is a presumption in criminal law and procedure that proof of mens rea or guilty mind is required in order to establish guilt.

Strict liability is in general terms liability without fault, so that all that has to be proved against the accused is the actus reus of the offence, no proof of mens rea being required. In such cases it will not be a defence to say 'I did not mean to break the law'. In appropriate cases this can be specifically stated, for example:

It is not a defence to a charge under this section that the accused person did not intend or foresee the consequences of his or her actions.

However, strict liability is not usually spelled out in this way, but is to be inferred where offences are of a regulatory nature, involving public health, welfare or safety, or involving such things as minor traffic violations, sale of impure food, violations of liquor laws, pollution of rivers and the environment generally, etc.

In some jurisdictions, a distinction is drawn between 'strict liability', where certain basic defences such as honest mistake of fact are available, and 'absolute liability', where no defence at all is available to the doing of the act which contravenes the provision (unless expressly provided in it). An example of an 'absolute offence':

A person commits an offence if he or she remains in Utopia after the expiry of a temporary residence permit and without having applied for and been granted an extension.
An offence under subsection (1) is committed whether or not the person knows that:

the permit has expired; or
no application for an extension has been made on his or her behalf or granted.

14.5 Shifting the burden of proof

In general, the burden of proof, that is of proving each of the necessary elements constituting the offence, will lie on the prosecution, but the burden of proving a defence or exception to the general rule is often placed on the defence. This is generally where the offence concerns doing something without the authority of a licence or permit, or in circumstances where an explanation, which only the person accused could give, is absent:

A person who, without lawful authority or excuse, deposits anything on the highway, in consequence of which a person is injured or endangered, commits an offence.

A person who carries an offensive weapon in a public place without reasonable excuse, the burden of proving which lies on that person, commits an offence.

In these cases, once the prosecution have proved the basic facts and direct or inferential absence of any authority or excuse it is for the defence to establish on the balance of probabilities that this did in fact exist. The rationale is that the prosecution would almost certainly be unable to positively prove absence of reasonable excuse (as opposed to leaving such lack of excuse to be inferred from the circumstances). Note also the burden of establishing a defence of lack of consent, etc. in cases of a director, etc. of a company, etc. which has been found guilty of an offence, referred to in section 14.3.1.

14.6 General matters concerning offences and penalties

14.6.1 Fixed penalties

It is the constitutional duty of the courts in criminal cases to enquire into matters alleged against persons and, if they are found to have been proved, to do justice as appropriate.

It has already been noted (section 14.1) that in the absence of specific provision to the contrary, sentences provided for offences are to be read as the maximum sentences available. It is accepted that it is for Parliament to lay down the highest penalty available to a court, but subject to that to leave to the discretion of the court the actual sentence that is appropriate in each individual case.

Normally the only exception is the mandatory imposition of the death penalty by a court on those found guilty of the most serious offences (murder, and in some jurisdictions armed robbery and certain serious drugs offences). Even here, the imposition of the death penalty will be subject to certain exceptions (e.g. where the convicted person is under a certain age, or a pregnant woman) and to the possible exercise of the prerogative of mercy by the Head of State.

Apart from these cases, the imposition of fixed penalties is normally reserved for minor offences where the police or some other authority are empowered specifically to proceed in that way:

If a police officer of or above the rank of Inspector has reason to believe that a person has committed an offence specified in the Schedule, the officer may serve on that person a fixed penalty notice in the prescribed form that:

specifies the offence;
states that the person served may elect, as an alternative to having the matter tried by a court, to pay a fine of $… to a specified court within 30 days.

If the fine is so paid, no proceedings may be brought against the person served with the notice in respect of that offence.

14.6.2 Minimum sentences

A sentence of this type would typically be drafted:

A person who commits an offence of handling stolen goods is liable to imprisonment for not less than 5 years.

While there is no constitutional reason why legislation should not provide for this kind of sentence, there are reasons why their provision in legislation should be discouraged:

they could remove a court's discretion to do justice in a particular case
courts dislike being constrained in this way and where they consider that imposition of a minimum sentence would work injustice they might seek:

ways of convicting an offender of an alternative offence (i.e. one where the sentence is at large, for example of theft instead of handling in the above case);
to acquit on a technicality.

14.6.3 Time limits on prosecutions

These apply normally only in cases of summary or minor offences (typically that an information must be laid before a magistrate within 6 months of the alleged offence taking place).

14.6.4 Written consent to prosecute

The express written consent of, for example, the Attorney General or the Director of Public Prosecutions is sometimes required, such as in politically sensitive cases, war crimes cases or cases with extra-territorial elements.

14.6.5 Fines as an alternative to imprisonment

Ideally, statutory or common law provisions will govern this, so that specific maximum alternative fines do not always have to be expressly provided. Where they are so provided, the relationship of maximum fine to maximum term of imprisonment should be reasonably consistent unless for special reasons (e.g. the financial nature of the offence itself; see also section 14.2.3) it is desired to provide a larger than usual financial penalty. The following would contravene this rule, as the maximum fine is small but the sentence of imprisonment comparatively severe:

A person who commits an offence under this Act is liable to a fine of $500, or to imprisonment for 2 years, or both.

14.6.6 Unlimited fines

Where no express provision is made either in general or specific penalty provisions for a maximum fine, statutory or common law provisions will provide that the extent of a fine is unlimited but 'must not be excessive'. Clearly, the relevant sentence would in most circumstances be subject to appeal.

14.6.7 Imprisonment in default of payment of a fine

A statutory scale is often set out (typically in a Criminal Procedure Act), but if it is not the same considerations would apply as under unlimited fines.

14.6.8 Attempts to commit offences

The common law rule that an attempt to commit an offence is itself an offence has been codified into the penal codes or equivalents in most jurisdictions, together with relevant penalties (either directly stated, or expressed as a proportion of the penalty for the full offence) and normally does not need to be provided for. Occasionally, however, the nature of the offence may warrant the express inclusion of attempts by way of clarification (see the Wildlife Protection Act example in section 14.6.9).

14.6.9 Statutory defences

There are a range of defences at common law, most of which are not normally drafted into offence provisions as they will be understood to apply. Indeed in some jurisdictions these have been codified into a Penal Code or Criminal Procedure Act. Most are in practice quite limited in their application, and some will clearly apply only to some offences:

claim of right (theft, burglary, trespass)
self-defence (homicide, assault)
mistake of fact
all due care
intoxication
insanity
duress
necessity.

However, it is sometimes desirable to draft specific defences that might apply in particular cases; these are known as statutory defences. It has already been seen that 'all due care' is usually drafted into a statutory defence by officers of corporations (section 14.3). A defence to a regulatory type of offence of strict liability might be drafted as follows:

It is a defence for a person charged to prove that the commission of the offence was due to a mistake or to an accident, or to some other cause beyond his or her control.

Sometimes explicit statutory defences are tailored to specific kinds of offence, as in the following example from a Wildlife Protection Act:

A person commits an offence if that person kills, injures or captures, or attempts to kill, injure or capture, a protected wild animal.
A person does not commit an offence under subsection (1) by reason only of:

unavoidably or accidentally killing or injuring the animal as an incidental result of a lawful action;
capturing or attempting to capture the animal where it has been injured, otherwise than by that person's illegal act, solely in order to tend it; or
killing or attempting to kill the animal where it appears to be so seriously injured, otherwise than by that person's illegal act, that to kill it would be an act of mercy.

14.6.10 Compounding of offences

Express powers need to be given for compounding of offences, as they will not be inferred. These powers are commonly included in legislation dealing with customs, banking and insurance, and traffic, and they are increasingly provided for regulatory offences (see section 14.4) and environmental offences.

They normally operate only where there has been an admission of guilt by the offender, and there should be an option for the offender to choose to appear before a court. There are obvious advantages for both enforcers and offenders. For the former, there is a quick and inexpensive alternative to prosecution; for the latter, the advantage of not having to go to court and not having the compounded offence recorded as a conviction in a criminal record. The devices are not appropriate for complex offences or where they are likely to be used as levers to induce admissions of guilt.

Subject to this section, the Commissioner for Customs and Excise may, if satisfied that a person has committed an offence under this Act in respect of which a penalty of a fine is provided, compound the offence and order that person to pay such sum of money as the Commissioner may think fit, not exceeding the amount of the fine to which the person would have been liable if he or she had been prosecuted and convicted of the offence.
The Commissioner may exercise the power under subsection (1) only if the person admits in writing that he or she has committed the offence and requests the Commissioner to deal with the offence accordingly.
Where the Commissioner makes an order under this section:

the order:

is to be in writing and have attached to it the request in writing of the person made under subsection (2);
is to specify the offence committed by the person and the penalty imposed by the Commissioner;

a copy of the order must be given to the person if he or she so requests;
on payment of the sum of money specified in the order the person is not liable to prosecution in respect of the offence.

The compounding of an offence under this section does not affect the liability to forfeiture of anything in relation to which the offence was committed.

It will be seen that there is some similarity between the procedure for compounding offences and that for fixed penalties above. The consequences of each will depend on how the provisions are drafted, although usually the payment of a fixed penalty does not alter the fact that an offence has been committed, and consequences such as penalty points on a driving licence (see section 14.7) could well follow. On the other hand, where an offence is compounded, the effect is usually that an offence is not recorded as such against the person in respect of whom the compounding order is made.

The concept of compounding offences has been enlarged considerably in recent years (see further section 14.8).

14.7 Other matters consequent on conviction

Consideration often needs to be given to drafting rules for the following types of consequences of conviction of an offence:

attachment of penalty points to a licence
cancellation or suspension of a licence
disqualification

If the court is to have power to order these, explicit provisions to that effect need to be inserted into the relevant legislation. They would be likely only in cases where the matter is clear-cut (as with, for example, driving offences) and would not involve, for example, assessment of a person's professional fitness to hold a licence, etc. Cases involving such an assessment would be better dealt with under the disciplinary powers given to statutory bodies to oversee the conduct of professions.

forfeiture

The court may order that any weapon or instrument in respect of which an offence has been proved is to be forfeited.

This would normally apply to articles that are the subject of, or produced in evidence at, criminal trials in which the accused person is convicted of unauthorised or otherwise criminal possession. The Interpretation Act will often provide that anything ordered to be forfeited will be forfeited to the Government.

seizure of assets

Separate legislation authorising this would normally be needed.

payment of compensation

Where a person is convicted of an offence, the court may order that person to pay compensation to a person who has suffered loss or damage as a result of the offence.

14.8 Administrative penalties

Administrative penalties are a mechanism for enforcing compliance with regulatory legislation, the use of which has significantly increased in recent years. They are monetary penalties assessed and imposed by a Minister or regulator without recourse to a court or administrative tribunal, and technically constitute a form of civil administrative, rather than criminal, proceedings.

An administrative penalty is a financial penalty that can be imposed on an individual or company that fails to comply with a particular provision of legislation, or the terms of an authorisation such as a permit or licence. As an administrative (or civil) rather than criminal type of sanction, administrative penalties are calculated and imposed by a Minister or designated Government official instead of a court of law. They are intended to encourage regulatory compliance. The following is a simple example of such a provision:

23 (1) If the regulator is satisfied on a balance of probabilities that a person has:

contravened a provision of this Act or the regulations,
failed to comply with an order under this Act, or
failed to comply with a requirement of a licence, certificate or permit issued, or notice given, under this Act,

the regulator may serve the person with a determination requiring the person to pay an administrative penalty in the amount specified in the determination.
A determination under subsection (1) must be in the prescribed form and contain the prescribed information.
Where a requirement to pay a penalty notice is issued under subsection (1), a prosecution for an offence under this Act in respect of the same contravention or failure may not be brought against the person.

A common instance of the use of this device has been in the area of benefit fraud:

This section applies where:

it appears to the Minister that there are grounds for instituting proceedings against a person for an offence under this Act relating to an act or omission on the part of that person in relation to a benefit; or
if an overpayment attributable to the act or omission had been made, the overpayment would have been recoverable from the person by, or due from the person to, the Treasury.

The Minister may give the person a written notice:

stating that the person may be invited to agree to pay a penalty and that, if he or she does so in the manner specified by the Minister, no proceedings referred to in subsection (1) will be instituted against him or her; and
containing such information relating to the operation of this section as may be prescribed.

If the person agrees in the specified manner to pay the penalty:

the amount of the penalty is recoverable by the same methods as those by which the overpayment is recoverable; and
no proceedings may be instituted against the person for an offence under this Act relating to the overpayment or to the act or omission referred to in subsection (1).

7327

7327.pdf 6 2026-03-13T06:58:18.146160 1

Chapter 19 Licensing Legislation

19.1 Introduction

In public law administration, two kinds of system are commonly used in order to authorise the carrying on of an activity that would otherwise be prohibited: licensing and registration.

A licence is a legal device by which permission is granted, in public law terms normally by the Government or a public authority, by means of some form of official document to carry on the activity. A simple form of licence is often referred to as a permit. Registration is a process used for official recording of persons and/or activities in an authoritative list.

Registration usually would, and licensing might, involve the person concerned satisfying certain legally prescribed requirements. Registration might even be automatic in those circumstances.

Both systems could run concurrently, as it is not uncommon for:

a register to be required of those persons to whom licences have been granted or
a licence (often in the form of a practising certificate) to be required to be taken out by those who have been registered.

19.2 The purposes of licensing and registration

The following principal purposes can be identified:

the laying down of minimum standards or qualifications for the carrying out of a specified activity, with which applicants must comply
creating official awareness of those engaged in the relevant activity
continuing supervision of an activity
control of the numbers of those engaged in a particular activity
the raising of public revenue, or recouping of administrative costs involved.

Legislative counsel needs to establish clearly whether the purpose of the scheme involves one or more of the following:

to enable a selection process to operate

merely as to suitability or
with the added intention of limiting numbers to be authorised

to enable a check to be kept on prescribed activities
to raise revenue
to control activities which involve danger or represent a threat or potential nuisance to a section of the public
to protect a resource so that it is not exhausted or overused.

While there may be good arguments in favour of a licensing regime, the counter-arguments also need to be kept in mind, and counsel needs, in appropriate cases, to be prepared to ask searching questions to clarify that policy-makers have considered the following potential problems:

it involves administration, and hence the creation of an extra bureaucracy
if not properly administered it can be a source of delay, expense and frustration to those affected
it can be used as a vehicle for discrimination and corruption.

19.3 The contents of licensing legislation

Specific provisions need to be made for introducing a licensing system, as the power to do so will not be implied in a general power to control or regulate activities. The following are some of the main incidents of licensing, although the order in which they appear will not necessarily follow the order below.

19.3.1 The licensing/registration authority

Is an existing authority (e.g. a Minister, a local government authority, the police, the Central Bank) to be given the power, or is it necessary to establish one for the purpose? The latter course is more likely in the case of a registration regime.

19.3.2 The activity to be regulated

The Act must state with precision the activity or activities to be regulated and make it a criminal offence to carry on the activity unless registered or licensed:

A person who carries on the business of providing transportation services to the public without being the holder of a licence under this Act commits an offence.

Sometimes there is need for an ancillary offence such as falsely holding oneself out as being registered or licensed.

19.3.3 Application

The person or authority to whom, and the way in which, application is to be made must be provided for. Often application is required to be made in a standard form prescribed either in the Act or subsidiary legislation. The section concerned might be the place to set out any required qualifications or any disqualifications.

In cases where the grant of a licence might be a matter of public concern (e.g. liquor, gaming) there would need to be provisions for giving notice of an application and for objections to be lodged. In addition, in cases where there is a considerable risk of malpractice, the authority might want to require the giving of security.

19.3.4 Criteria for grant

These would depend very much on the type of licence granted. In a simple revenue-gathering exercise (e.g. television or motor vehicle licences), the criteria can be set out in the legislation, so that the grant will be automatic on payment of the requisite fee. But in many cases the suitability of the applicant will be a matter for assessment. Clearly this will involve a discretion in the authority to grant or refuse:

A person applying for registration under this Act must satisfy the Board that he or she:

(a) is of good character and reputation;
(b) is resident in Utopia; and
(c) holds an approved professional qualification.

19.3.5 Processing of the application

Procedure is normally a matter of administration rather than law, but in cases where a person’s livelihood or reputation might be adversely affected by refusal to grant, a right to be heard in person, or at least to make written representations, might be required. Courts would be likely in these cases to hold that the rules of natural justice require it. Provisions might be necessary relating, for example, to informing the applicant in writing of the reasons for refusal, particularly if there is to be an appeal procedure, or to giving the applicant the opportunity of making representations in person:

Before refusing an application for a licence the Council must give the person making the application an opportunity of appearing before, and making representations to, a committee of the Council.

19.3.6 Imposing of conditions

Where specified or prescribed conditions are to attach to a licence of a particular kind, these should be set out in the Act or subsidiary legislation. If the authority is to have the power to impose other conditions, there would need to be an express power to allow it to do so (it would be unsafe to leave such an important power to have to be argued as being a necessary incidental one).

A licensing authority may attach conditions and limitations to licences in addition to those provided for in regulations, but not in a manner inconsistent with this Act or the regulations.

19.3.7 Duration and renewal

Unless a licence is for a particular occasion (sometimes called an ‘occasional licence’), the duration period (commonly one year from the date of issue) must be provided for, probably in the Act. Provisions relating to renewal must be set out, particularly where these differ from those on original application (e.g. because a more streamlined procedure is to be involved). This aspect of things does not normally apply with respect to registration.

19.3.8 Variation

If the power to vary is required (e.g. to reflect a change in business premises) it should be stated.

The Authority may, by written notice, require the holder of a licence to return it to the Authority within 14 days to enable the licence to be amended.

If that power is exercisable by the authority of its own motion (e.g. to add conditions to a licence), then a procedure consistent with natural justice, for example provisions relating to prior notification, and the opportunity to make representations, probably need also to be included.

19.3.9 Suspension, revocation and surrender

These powers are not necessarily to be implied in a power to register or grant a licence but should be expressly dealt with. Again, principles of natural justice would normally require that the person to be affected be given an opportunity to make representations. In cases of surrender, actual delivery up of the document might not always be required unless, for example, in cases where a refund of part of a licence fee is available.

19.3.10 Transfer

A licence is normally personal to the grantee, but some licences, particularly those of a revenue-gathering character (e.g. a motor vehicle licence), or where the licensee dies, may be transferable:

On the death of the holder of a licence, the personal representatives of the deceased are to be treated as the holders of the licence for 3 months from the date of death or any longer period the licensing authority may approve.

Provision should be made for conditions, if any, which are to apply to transfer (e.g. notification, possibly in a prescribed manner, to the authority).

19.3.11 Appeals

If provided for, these would apply in cases of refusal to register, or grant or renew a licence. An appeal procedure would normally be confined to cases where the applicant or licensee stands to lose economically or in reputation. The matter of exactly who has the right to appeal (is it to be extended to persons other than those directly affected?), the grounds, the appeal authority, the time limitation applicable and the powers of the appellate authority need to be provided for.

19.3.12 Display and production for inspection

If there are precise requirements for display, these must be set out. Apart from these, there would normally need to be some fairly good reason to require production for inspection (e.g. suspicion of conducting a regulated business without a licence).

19.3.13 Inspection of register

The issue of whether or not a register is to be open for public inspection must be considered. Are there public interest issues bearing on the matter?

19.3.14 Enforcement

Powers of appointment of inspectors, and of entry and inspection of documents relating to the licensed or registered activity, might be required, with offences and penalties in respect of obstruction.

19.3.15 Subsidiary legislation

Procedural arrangements, prescription of fees and forms, and other administrative details, are commonly left to be dealt with by subsidiary legislation.

19.4 Typical transitional and savings provisions relating to licences

19.4.1 Automatic grant of licence, or registration, in certain cases

If a person who was an operator of a retirement home immediately before the commencement of this Act applies in the prescribed manner for a licence under section 5 within 60 days of the commencement:

(a) the licensing authority must then issue a licence to that person in respect of the premises in which he or she was operating; but
(b) the provisions of this Act operate [note: not shall operate] in respect of that licence.

Where at the commencement of this Act a person was practising accountancy, and had been continuously so practising for not less than 5 years immediately before commencement, that person is to be taken to be qualified under section 26 and is entitled to be registered under this Act.

19.4.2 Time to be granted to apply

A person who immediately before the coming into force of this Act was operating a zoo may continue to operate that zoo without a licence under this Act:

(a) for a period of 6 months beginning with that date; and
(b) if within that period he or she applies for a licence, until that application is finally disposed of or withdrawn and, if the application is refused, for a further period of 6 months from the date of refusal.

19.4.3 Postponement of operation of law

A person must not, after a period of 6 months from the date of the commencement of this Act, carry on business as a tourist guide...

19.4.4 Temporary option to choose law

During the period of 3 months from the commencement of this Act, a person who wants to begin constructing, altering or demolishing a building may, at that person’s option, apply:

(a) for a building permit under this Act; or
(b) for the permit that would have been required if this Act had not come into force, in which case the application is to be dealt with as though this Act had not come into force.

7329

7329.pdf 7 2026-03-13T07:00:39.776737 1

Appendix A: Legislative Procedure and Preparation

A typical Government directive applicable to a small Commonwealth jurisdiction

References are made below to the Prime Minister, but they apply equally to the President or Head of Government however styled.

Part I Bills

Proposals for legislation

1(1) Where proposals for legislation are initiated within a Ministry they are the responsibility of the Minister holding the portfolio. Where they are initiated within a special Department they are the responsibility of the Minister to whom responsibility for that Department is assigned by the Prime Minister, who must be approached by the Head of Department with a view to obtaining his or her decision about whether the legislation is necessary.

(2) Where a Minister considers that new or amending legislation by Act of Parliament is necessary, interested persons and bodies should be consulted wherever possible, and a Cabinet Memorandum asking for approval in principle must be submitted by the Minister to the Cabinet.

(3) The Cabinet Memorandum must set out the principles of the policy intended to be carried into effect by the proposed Bill, and the reasons why it is considered necessary, but it should not go into detail as to changes in existing law that will be needed. It must also state the classification of the proposed Bill. The classifications are:

URGENT – to be introduced at the current meeting of Parliament;
PRIORITY A – to be introduced at the next meeting;
PRIORITY B – to be introduced at the next meeting but one;
PRIORITY C – to be introduced at some later time.

(4) Wherever possible a draft of the Cabinet Memorandum should be sent in advance to the Law Officers so that they may advise on whether an Act of Parliament is in fact necessary in order to achieve the objects desired, and on other legal aspects of the proposal.

Approval in principle

2(1) The Secretary to the Cabinet will as soon as possible notify the Department concerned and the Law Officers of the Cabinet’s decision on an application for approval in principle.

(2) Where approval in principle is given, the head of the Ministry concerned will send Drafting Instructions to the Law Officers for the drafting of the Bill.

(3) Except in cases of extreme urgency, or for other exceptional reasons, instructions for the drafting of a Bill must not be given unless Cabinet’s approval in principle has been obtained.

Drafting instructions

3(1) Drafting instructions must contain:

full details of the policy intended to be carried into effect by the Bill
references to the enactments proposed to be repealed or amended
an indication of the priority of the Bill as determined by the Cabinet

(2) Drafting Instructions should be accompanied by the relevant memoranda, reports of committees, and any other material which may be useful to legislative counsel. Draft Bills should not be sent as Drafting Instructions, but may, in exceptional cases (such as where the subject matter of the intended legislation is of a highly technical nature), be included.

Legislative programme

4(1) About two months before each meeting of Parliament, the Prime Minister’s Office will circulate a request for a list of the Bills proposed to be introduced during that meeting and at subsequent meetings by each Minister. The returns from Ministries will be consolidated and submitted to the Cabinet Legislation Committee, which will prepare for Cabinet approval a programme for the forthcoming meeting and subsequent meetings. The order of priority for each Bill is decided by the Cabinet.

(2) With the approval of the Cabinet, legislation which is not included in the programme may be introduced during the meeting if the need should arise, but this should as far as possible be avoided, since in such cases there is seldom time for full consideration of the drafting of the Bill.

Hasty and ill-considered legislation is likely to contain errors which may interfere with its intended working and bring the law into disrepute.

Settlement of Draft Bills

5(1) After such discussions and clarification of the Drafting Instructions as legislative counsel may consider necessary, counsel will produce the first draft of the Bill. In the cases of long or complex Bills the first draft may be of only a particular segment of the Bill.

(2) Legislative counsel will send the first draft to the Ministry concerned and any other Departments which are interested in the subject matter of the Bill.

(3) All persons to whom a draft Bill or part of a Bill is sent should scrutinise the Bill with care to make sure that it gives effect to the policy desired. It should not be assumed that, because a Bill has been drafted by legislative counsel, it does not require scrutiny in this way. It may happen that there has been some misunderstanding over the legislative intent, or there may be other reasons for corrections in the draft. However, alterations to the text of the draft Bill must in no circumstance be made otherwise than by legislative counsel.

Memorandum to the Bill

6. The Standing Orders of Parliament require every Bill to be accompanied by a Memorandum to the Bill signed by the Minister introducing the Bill, explaining its main features. The Ministry concerned should settle the wording of the Memorandum to the Bill, but legislative counsel should be consulted to ensure that the Memorandum correctly describes its contents.

Cabinet approval of Draft Bill

7(1) When the form of the Bill has been agreed between the sponsoring Ministry and legislative counsel, the Minister responsible will submit it to the Cabinet for final approval and for permission to introduce the Bill in Parliament. The sponsoring Ministry must forward to the Secretary to the Cabinet a memorandum by the Minister seeking this approval and permission, together with the requisite number of copies of the draft Bill.

(2) The Secretary to the Cabinet will normally forward a copy of the Minister’s memorandum and the Cabinet’s decision on it to the Law Officers so that a record can be kept of the Bills which have been approved for introduction.

Publication of Draft Bill

8(1) Except where the Certificate of Urgency procedure is to be used, the sponsoring Ministry should arrange for the publication of the Bill as soon as possible after Cabinet permission has been given. The Standing Orders of Parliament require a certain interval to elapse between the publication and introduction of the draft Bill unless the Certificate of Urgency procedure is followed. Seven clear days must elapse between the day on which the sitting commences and the day on which the Bill is to be introduced. If a Bill is published before or during a meeting and is not introduced at a subsequent meeting within one month of the original publication, that Bill must be re-published.

(2) The Bill must be published as a supplement to the Gazette.

(3) Only one Gazette publication is necessary, but since it is essential that all Members of Parliament should have had as much opportunity as possible to study the text of a Bill before it is debated in Parliament, the notice prescribed by the Standing Orders is regarded as the minimum. Normally, considerably more notice should be given.

(4) It is sometimes the case that a Bill prepared at the instance of one Ministry and designed for a particular purpose affects other Ministries, or is one to which an amendment could be moved to deal with minor points with which other Ministries are concerned. It is important therefore that all Ministries should study Bills published in the Gazette, as well as paying careful attention to the legislative programme generally.

(5) The Standing Orders of Parliament permit alterations to be made in the Bill as published if those are of a trivial or drafting character. The alterations are made when the blue copies of the Bill as introduced are printed. Since this procedure avoids the need for formal amendments in Parliament it should be used wherever necessary.

Certificate of Urgency Procedure

9(1) The Standing Orders provide that a Bill mentioned in a Certificate of Urgency, signed by the Prime Minister, may be introduced without publication or distribution to Members of Parliament, and may be taken through all its stages in one day.

(2) Where a Bill has to be introduced under a Certificate of Urgency, the Ministry concerned should make the necessary arrangements with the Secretary to the Cabinet, and should inform legislative counsel without delay. The Ministry should also inform the Prime Minister’s Office of the date on which the Certificate has been sent to the Speaker.

(3) It is emphasised that this procedure for the introduction of a Bill is for use in emergency only and is to be avoided as much as possible. In order to achieve its purpose of giving effect to government policies, legislation needs to be prepared with care and due consideration. Legislation put through in haste and without adequate publicity is likely to prove defective.

Passage of Bill

10(1) The progress of a Bill in Parliament is governed by the Standing Orders of Parliament which provide for four main stages. The First Reading, which is purely formal, takes place when the Minister responsible for the Bill rises in place and bows to the Chair, and the clerk reads aloud the Long Title. The Second Reading, involves consideration of the principles and general merits of the Bill. The Bill then passes through the Committee Stage (also known as the Consideration Stage ), at which the details of the Bill may be considered and amendments made. Normally two sitting days must elapse between Second Reading and Consideration Stage .

(2) The Bill is treated as having been passed when it receives the Third Reading, which normally cannot take place earlier than the next but one sitting day after the Committee Stage. The periods between stages prescribed by Standing Orders should be regarded as the minimum. Normally in a Bill of any length or one which is controversial there should be an interval of approximately a week between the Second Reading Stage and the Committee Stage, and all Government amendments should be put as early as possible.

(3) The sponsoring Ministry should take careful note of the progress of the Bill through Parliament, and a representative of the Ministry should be present at the Second Reading Stage and the Committee Stage. Legislative counsel should also attend. The Weekly Business Statement, which is normally given in Parliament on Fridays, will usually indicate when a particular stage of a Bill is to be taken. Reference may also be made to the agenda and provisional agenda of Parliament.

Assent

11(1) When a Bill has been passed by Parliament the Clerk of Parliament will follow the relevant procedures laid down and submit Presentation Copies to the Head of State for the Assent.

(2) Where the Assent has been given, it is the responsibility of the Clerk of Parliament to number the Presentation Copies. One copy is retained by the Prime Minister’s Office and the Prime Minister’s Office should forward the remaining copies one each to the Chief Justice, the Speaker and the Archivist.

Publication

12. As soon as possible after Assent, the Act should be published in the Gazette. The avoidance of delay may be of particular importance where a Bill has been introduced under a Certificate of Urgency. Unless the Act otherwise provides, it comes into force at the commencement of the day following the day on which the Assent is signified, or as provided by the Constitution, or on the date of publication. The date of Assent will appear at the beginning of each Act. Where an Act provides that it should come into force on a date to be determined, the initiative for obtaining Cabinet approval for its date of commencement rests with the sponsoring Ministry.

Part II Subsidiary Legislation

Cabinet Approval

13. Where it is proposed to make subsidiary legislation, the Minister concerned should, subject to the directions given by the Prime Minister, decide whether Cabinet approval for the making of the instrument is necessary. Where Cabinet approval is considered necessary, a Cabinet Memorandum asking for this must be submitted by the Minister to the Cabinet.

Drafting

14(1) Subject to the directions given by the Cabinet or the Minister responsible, the Head of a Ministry should decide whether subsidiary legislation is to be drafted within the Ministry or by legislative counsel. Except in special cases, executive instruments will be drafted within the Ministry concerned, but with any necessary assistance of legislative counsel.

(2) Where an instrument is to be drafted by legislative counsel, Drafting Instructions must be sent to the Law Officers. These must contain full details of the policy intended to be carried into effect by the instrument and should be accompanied by the relevant memoranda and any other material which may be useful to legislative counsel. Subject to the necessary modifications, paragraph 5 relating to the settlement of draft Bills applies in relation to instruments drafted by legislative counsel.

(3) Where subsidiary legislation has not been drafted by legislative counsel it must be submitted in draft to the Law Officers so that its validity and form may be checked before it is made.

(4) All subsidiary legislation intended for publication must be in the form required by the relevant legislation.

Making of subsidiary legislation

15. Subsidiary legislation is made when it is signed by the Head of State or the Minister responsible. The procedure laid down by the relevant legislation should be followed.

Publication

16(1) All subsidiary legislation must be published in the Gazette. The Ministry concerned should send a copy of the instrument to the Government Printer for publication.

(2) Where a legislative instrument or executive instrument is sent to the Government Printer for publication, the officer concerned must ensure that it is in the proper form and must indicate whether the instrument is a legislative instrument or an executive instrument.

(3) Unless the instrument otherwise provides, a legislative instrument comes into operation on the date of Gazette notification. This date is printed at the end of the instrument. An executive instrument comes into operation on the day on which it is made.

7332

7332.pdf 6 2026-03-13T07:03:37.708124 1

Appendix D: Suggested Approaches to Translation of Policy

Legislative counsel will first of all need to be satisfied as to the type of legislation to be employed (this and associated matters are referred to in Chapter 11). From there it is a question of the detailed analysis of the policy. Apart from the use of the ‘six serving men’, and the requirement to ensure that as far as possible the matters referred to in the ‘6 Cs’ of effective communication (both referred to in Chapter 2) apply, there can be no universal guide to the analysis required to effectively translate a particular policy into an effective legislative rule or series of rules. Obviously, each will depend on its own particular set of circumstances.

However, there follow two instances of simple policy statements and how legislative counsel might approach each of them:

Policy 1: Wildlife in nature sanctuaries to be protected

Firstly counsel would need to consider the broader aspects of the policy by asking fundamental questions about it:

Why? Environmental conservation.
Who? Anybody who is inside a sanctuary.
What ... exactly is being protected? Unless instructed about specific exceptions, counsel must assume this means all animal, and coral and plant life (including what might be termed as vermin, for e.g. rats).
How ... is protection to operate? Presumably this is to be by a complete ban on killing, injuring or damaging the animal and plant life.

Where? Obviously the protection is to apply within each sanctuary. Firstly counsel will need to establish to what kinds of area the policy is to apply. Do ‘sanctuaries’ included national wildlife parks or reserves, about which there may already be legislation? Or are they to be contained in legislation at a more local level (e.g. for local parks or wildlife sanctuaries)? This will probably be apparent from the nature of the instructions, but counsel might need to consider whether a definition of ‘nature sanctuary’ or ‘wildlife sanctuary’ is required.

Presumably the protection also applies to animals in, and plants growing in, a sanctuary that are accessible from outside it. ^165

Having satisfied himself or herself as to the above, there is no rule as to how counsel should now proceed, but it is often a good idea to produce a first draft. This can then serve as a basis for further analysis and refinement. The following assumes that the sanctuary is a land rather than a marine one.

First draft

A person must not kill, injure or cause damage to an animal or plant in a nature sanctuary.

Policy analysis refinements

‘Animal’ is capable of more than one meaning, depending on the context in which the word is used:

mammals
mammals, reptiles and amphibians (i.e. not birds, fish or invertebrates)
all animal (as opposed to plant) life.

Presumably here the third of these is intended (i.e. to include birds, fish, insects, spiders, molluscs, snails, worms, etc.) and if so the term needed will be ‘animal life’. As regards plants, instructions might be needed with regard to whether a definition is required to include, for example, fungi or seaweed, and it might be helpful to refer to larger plants (trees and shrubs) specifically.

Is the list of prohibited conduct exhaustive? Where animal life is concerned, capturing obviously needs also to be included, even where this action causes no injury. Furthermore, at a more subtle level, a ban would also be needed on behaviour that might frighten or disturb animals, especially if it is likely to affect their feeding or ability to breed.

Where plant life is concerned, there are activities that do not necessarily damage a plant that also probably need to be banned, namely removal in whole or part (e.g. some roots or branches), or picking flowers or fruit from it.

And what about domesticated animals that may wander into the sanctuary? Presumably the protection is not intended to apply to them, especially where they are, for example, farm animals that have escaped. Does the same consideration need to be given to domesticated plants (this is possible but less likely)?

How can distinction be made in a rule between what is a domestic animal or plant and what is not? Probably the expression ‘in the wild’ will cover the latter.

In the light of all these further considerations, counsel would be ready to produce a revised draft.

Revised draft

A person must not:

kill, injure, capture, remove or disturb animal life occurring in the wild in a wildlife sanctuary;
destroy, damage, uproot or remove the whole or part of a tree, shrub or other plant growing in a wildlife sanctuary.

There are two particular points to note with regard to this. Firstly, the legal subject (see Chapter 4) is ‘a person’, not ‘a person in a wildlife sanctuary’; hence, the application to those who might do something prohibited from outside the sanctuary itself. Secondly, the expression ‘occurring in the wild’ applies only in paragraph (a), meaning that protection for domesticated plants as well as wild ones would be afforded.

Policy 2: No standing on the bus

Here the basic policy analysis is simple:

Why? Safety of passengers.
Who? Applies to passengers, not, for example, bus company personnel.
When? The bus is moving.
Where? Inside the bus (not literally ‘on’ top of it), but ‘on’ conveys that idea

As in the previous example, an initial rough draft might help to focus on the problems.

First draft

A passenger on a bus must not stand while the bus is moving

Policy analysis refinements

It does not take much thought to see that further clarification and refinement is needed. Firstly, with regard to the obligation not to stand, is it acceptable if, for example, passengers sit, crouch or lie on the floor, or on the seats?

Almost certainly not. In this case it is therefore far more effective to state what passengers are required to do (i.e. sit on a passenger seat) than what they are required not to do.

Secondly, does the rule mean literally no standing at any time while the bus is moving? Is it acceptable if passengers are standing while the bus is moving off if they have not yet reached their seats, or if they are preparing to get off the bus?

The practical answer to this question must be yes, meaning that some kind of exception needs to be considered.

Is the rule to be drafted for all buses whenever they contain passengers (including, for example, buses on private charter or hire), or only buses for use by the public (i.e. on scheduled service)? In the latter case, would the same rules apply to urban bus services as to inter-city bus services? These things would of course depend on the policy instructions, although it is likely that the rule would apply only to buses for use by the public. Private hire would in this sort of area probably be governed by the relevant hire agreement.

Having done the further analysis, it is now usually helpful to make a first rough draft that can be gradually refined in terms of precision and style. Making the assumption that the rule is to apply to passengers on a scheduled service, and also that an exception needs to be made in respect of getting on or off the bus. It can be seen that there are a number of alternative words and phrases that can be used:

A passenger on a bus must [sit] [remain seated] on a passenger seat while the bus is [moving] [in motion], unless in the process of [getting on or off] [embarking on to or disembarking from] the bus.

This first draft of a rule (when a stylistic decision is made as to particular words or phrases to be used) will create, when penal provisions relating to contravention are added, a straightforward offence.

Refinement of the rule

But further consideration is needed as to how practicable (that is, easy to enforce) the rule will be. This can easily be tested by asking what happens if a passenger fails to comply?

Such a situation could arise by way of deliberate refusal to sit, even though there is a seat available, although in practice it would be more likely where, having been allowed on the bus, the person concerned finds that there is in fact no such seat. If a person, after a request to do so, fails (as the case requires) either to sit or to leave the bus, the driver (if he or she is not simply to ignore the contravention) is going to have to stop the bus and attempt to manhandle the offender off it, or call a bus inspector or the police to the scene. The latter course would almost certainly be time-consuming and highly annoying for other passengers, and supposes both that the driver would have a radio or telephone and that the inspector or police are easily locatable.

So can the rule be strengthened to get round this problem? The neatest way would be by giving the driver express powers to direct a passenger who fails to sit as required or to get off, and to control the number of persons getting on. That initially produces two rules:

If a passenger refuses to sit on a passenger seat, the driver may [direct] [require] that person to [leave] [disembark from] the bus.

If all passenger seats are occupied the driver may [direct] [require] a person for whom there is no seat not to [get on] [enter] the bus or to [get off] [disembark from] it.

As the power to require a person to leave the bus is common to both these rules, the draft could be improved slightly by combining the two sentences and by using paragraphs:

The driver may direct a person not to enter the bus or, having entered, to leave it if:

all the passenger seats are occupied; or
the person fails to occupy a passenger seat when one is available.

All that remains then is to draft the necessary penal provisions. As this is a low-level offence (it would probably exist in bye-laws), it is likely that the maximum sentence would consist of a fine only.

Putting all the elements together and polishing the draft in the process, the rule makes the assumption that the buses concerned are controlled by a driver alone:

Bus passengers to remain seated

A passenger on a bus must remain seated on a passenger seat while the bus is moving, unless he or she is in the process of embarking or disembarking.
The driver may direct a person to not to enter the bus or, having entered, to leave it if:

all the passenger seats are occupied; or
the person, being a passenger, fails to occupy a passenger seat when one is available.

A person who contravenes paragraph (1), or who fails to comply with a direction of a driver under paragraph (2), commits an offence and is liable to a fine of $500.

In paragraph (2) it can be noted that a distinction has to be made between a person who is not yet a passenger and one who is (having paid a fare or used or displayed some kind of pass). Practical difficulties might arise in a case where a person is mistakenly admitted as a passenger, and provision made for a refund or credit of any fare paid.

Although an offence is created under both paragraphs (1) and (2), in practice any prosecution would probably be under (2). However, paragraph (1) is still needed to set out the full context of the rule.

Appendix E

Suggested Approaches to Drafting

Attention is drawn in this Appendix to various practical matters which are of particular relevance to legislative counsel at the start of the actual drafting of a Bill

In the first draft, counsel will construct the Bill on the foundations worked out in the legislative scheme which has been prepared (see Chapter 11).
In drafting individual provisions, counsel is urged to have regard to the approaches to translation of policy suggested in Appendix D.
An interval of time should ideally be allowed to elapse between the completion of the first draft and the start of the revision stage. This interval will allow counsel to bring a fresh and clear mind to the revision and he or she will be able to detect more easily errors, omissions and inconsistencies in the first draft. Sentences can, for example, be restricted or made shorter, without obscuring the intended meaning of the sentence. Once the draft has been revised, it is desirable to ask a colleague or colleagues to read the draft critically.
If a colleague, on reading the draft, interprets it in a manner not intended by counsel this will indicate at once that some changes to it are needed. In some jurisdictions, it is the practice for counsel to work in pairs. Where this is not the case the draft should so far as possible be checked by at least one other person before it is sent to the sponsoring Ministry.
In most cases counsel will have to prepare a number of drafts before the finalised draft Bill is sent to the sponsoring Ministry. During the drafting process he or she must constantly check the draft with other laws and in particular with the Interpretation Act. A date should be inserted on each of the drafts and the earlier drafts saved. At a later date there may be a need to revert to wording that has been used in an earlier draft.
While the use of legislative precedents from other jurisdictions may be useful, it is discouraged as a basis for drafts. This is because precedents apply someone else’s thinking to a problem that may not be exactly the same as the one faced by counsel drafting the new provisions, and they can be misleading. If used they should act only as a check or comparison after counsel has prepared the necessary draft. Some specific provisions may need to be standardised within a jurisdiction, and to that extent a local precedent may be useful.
Even precedents from within the jurisdiction need to be used with care. While they might be useful as examples on how to draft the more formal provisions in a Bill to set up a statutory corporation, great care needs to be exercised to ensure that provisions are not included merely because they have been in the past; each must be clearly understood as having a valid function in the Bill being drafted.
However, an exception to the caution against the use of precedents would be the occasional cases where a model Act, such as those published from time to time by the Commonwealth Secretariat, has a direct bearing on the subject matter. Such models always refer to the necessity for adaptation of their provisions within a particular jurisdiction.
A careful check should be carried out to see whether any precedent being adapted has been the subject of a judicial decision or subsequent legislative amendment.
Where an adaptable precedent is found, counsel should be careful to make a note on the draft of the relevant reference. This may seem to be an obvious precaution to take, but in practice it is sometimes forgotten, with the result that valuable time and frustrating effort may later have to be spent in rediscovering the relevant precedent.
Legislation is used to solve a problem. The problem covered by a precedent may not be the precise problem being dealt with, and the policy or context may have changed since the precedent was enacted.
Counsel must check the draft carefully and ensure that it reads as a coherent and consistent whole. Words and expressions specifically defined in the interpretation clause of a Bill apply throughout the Bill. One way of ensuring that this is not overlooked is for counsel to underline or insert in bold type these words or expressions every time they are used. This will facilitate the requisite attention for the final revision of the draft.
In the first draft, counsel is primarily concerned with the coverage of the basic objectives of the proposed legislation and ensuring that practical difficulties in administering and enforcing it are sufficiently dealt with. At the revision stages, counsel must consider whether an improvement in the wording, style and arrangement can be achieved so that the legislation becomes more readable and intelligible to those persons most likely to be affected by it.
A great deal of legislation is by its very nature complicated. Counsel must remember that his or her first duty is to convey the legislative intention as clearly as possible to those to be affected. In so doing, he or she will have constant regard to the attributes of effective communication referred to in Chapter 2.
It is usual to publish with a Bill an explanatory memorandum which explains its objects and reasons. This is sometimes prepared by counsel and sometimes by the sponsoring Ministry. In the latter case it is obviously desirable that the Ministry consult counsel when preparing the memorandum, so that Parliament and the public are not misled as to the intended effect of the Bill.

Chapter 6 Plain Language Drafting

6.1 Introduction

The general Commonwealth trend has been to move away from the traditional drafting styles of the past involving the use of largely unfamiliar words and expressions and lengthy sentences, which were thought to be necessary in the interests of conveying precise meaning.

Recent changes in perception have recognised that legal writing generally, and legislation in particular, should be able as far as possible to be readily understood by those to be affected by it. It has come to be seen as a waste of resources for legal documents to have to be ‘translated’ into everyday language by lawyers. It has also come to be recognised that the former styles (sometimes mockingly known as ‘legalese’) can take on a life of their own, so that drafters using them can fall into patterns of both thought and writing that may cause a failure to adequately address the drafting problems.

There are still many people who remain unconvinced by some of these changes (including the move away from the auxiliary ‘shall’, discussed in Chapter 5), especially in more conservative jurisdictions and especially among some MPs and members of the legal profession. It may thus not be a matter of individuals (unless in very senior positions) being able to take it upon themselves to change things in the ways proposed. The introduction of new drafting practices is thus an issue that may require tact and perseverance.

6.2 Reasons why legislation may fail to communicate clearly

The most obvious of these is that legislative provisions are imprecise or difficult to understand because the thinking behind them is unclear:

(2) A person shall be deemed to deposit or dump waste under this Act if he deposits or dumps the waste, whether solid, semi-solid or liquid, in such circumstances, or for such period that he may be deemed:

to have abandoned it where it is deposited or dumped; or
to have brought it to the place where it is so deposited or dumped for the purpose of its being disposed of or abandoned whether by him or any other person.

See further the examples in section 6.4 relating to the passive voice and modifiers.

However, even though the thinking behind them is probably clear and the language attempts to be precise, they may still for various reasons be difficult to read and understand (see the other examples in section 6.4).

6.3 General objective of plain English in drafting legislation

To communicate more effectively with those to whom a document is addressed, and in doing so to:

use language that is simple, direct, economical and familiar
omit unnecessary or repetitious words or phrases
use sentence structures that avoid ambiguity or undue complexity
organise and present sentences in a way that enables their meaning to be grasped as quickly as possible.

6.4 The most common specific problems that need to be addressed

6.4.1 Excessively long sentences

Sentences that exceed 20 to 30 words present problems of understanding unless the text is broken up (see Chapter 7).

No action, suit, prosecution or other proceeding whatsoever shall lie or be brought, instituted or maintained in any court or before any other authority against the Government, a State Government, the Central Bank, any officer or employee of any such Government or of the Central Bank, either personally or in his official capacity, or any person lawfully acting on behalf of any such Government or the Central Bank, or on behalf of any such officer or employee, either personally or in his capacity as a person acting on such behalf, for or on account of, or in respect of, any act done or statement made, or omitted to be done or made, or purporting to be done or made or omitted to be done or made, in pursuance or in execution of, or intended pursuance of, this Act, or any order in writing, direction, instruction, notice or other thing whatsoever issued under this Act.

Difficulty in reading and understanding this sentence arises because it is not concise and contains too many detailed and confusing references to persons and complex context conditions.

6.4.2 Legislative sentences do not follow standard English usage

Complex verb constructions or inconsistencies with modern grammatical practice make for difficulty in understanding, for example, different uses of the auxiliary ‘shall’ (see further Chapter 5); use of deeming provisions; and use of provisos:

A person who shall have received a fee for advising another person in relation to an investment shall be deemed to have advised that person in the course of business:
Provided that he shall not be deemed to have done so in the course of business if he shall prove that…

Rather state:

A person who receives a fee for advising another person about an investment is to be regarded as having done so in the course of business, unless the person advising proves that…

The word ‘deem’ in provisions that create a legal fiction or (as here) a rule of interpretation is slightly archaic and needs to be replaced by a modern equivalent such as that used in the example above (or others such as ‘be treated as’). Discouragement of the use of provisos will be considered further in Chapter 7 (‘Structuring legislative drafts’, section on grouping provisions). Note also that the redrafted version is in gender-neutral language (see further Chapter 10).

6.4.3 Use of archaic or pretentious words and expressions

Avoid meaningless or cumbersome words and expressions of reference or stress such as ‘aforesaid’, ‘hereby’, ‘hereinbefore mentioned’ and ‘whatsoever’. See further examples in the list at the end of this chapter.

Elements of the following hypothetical, and, by modern standards, slightly preposterous archaic writing, can still sometimes be seen:

15. (1) Whosoever^1 shall be^2 seised of^3 chattels real^4 to which the immediately preceding section of this Act^5 relates^6, shall not^7 utilise^8 the said chattels^9 for the purposes of^10 hire, reward^11 or sale before the expiration of^12 the hereinafter in this section mentioned^13 relevant period of time.

Modern use would be ‘A person (who)…’.
This is the future tense. The present tense should be used.
Archaic word for ‘possess’ in relation to leasehold property.
Archaic word for interests in land less than freehold (it usually refers to leaseholds).
A pretentious (and potentially confusing) reference, which should be to the relevant section number, and there is normally no need to use ‘of this Act’.
‘Refer’ is a more modern word.
‘Must’ and ‘must not’ are the auxiliaries in everyday use indicating obligation.
A pretentious form of ‘use’. Even that word can be avoided here.
‘The said’ is an archaic and unnecessary expression of reference.
‘For the purposes of’ means no more than ‘for’.
‘Hire or reward’ is a stock lawyer’s phrase. Consideration should be given to more apt or precise terms if possible.
A pretentious (and often used) alternative to ‘expiry of’ or ‘end of’.
Pretentious, clumsy and archaic style. In this context, it is apparent that the specification will be made later in section 15.

Rather, the proposition ought to be stated thus:

15. (1) A person in possession of leasehold premises referred to in section 14 must not offer them for subletting, mortgage or sale until the specified time period has ended.

6.4.4 Careless use of the passive voice

The potential danger caused by this has already been noted in Chapter 4 (section 4.1 on ‘Legal subject’). It is not suggested that this form of expression should be avoided altogether, but unthinking use can cause problems of understanding. The following example is from a Narcotic Drugs Act:

27. Where a medical practitioner is convicted of an offence under this Act, he shall be liable to have his name removed from the register of those licensed or registered to practice as a medical practitioner.

Here the drafter has not addressed his or her mind to who is to do the removing. Is it the registrar (no mention of whom is made in this particular Act), or is it the court? See further Chapter 14 (‘Penal provisions’).

On the other hand, the use of the passive would be convenient in the following example:

If a vessel is wrecked, stranded or in distress on or near the coast, any cargo or other article belonging to or separated from the vessel which is washed on shore or otherwise lost or taken from the vessel must be delivered to the receiver.

Here it is perfectly clear who is addressed by the rule (i.e. anyone finding cargo, etc., from a wreck, etc.) and to draft in the active voice would require many more words (58 as against 45):

If a vessel is wrecked, stranded or in distress on or near the coast, a person who comes into possession of the cargo or any part of it, or any other article belonging to or separated from the vessel which is washed on shore or otherwise lost or taken from the vessel must deliver it to the receiver.

6.4.5 Careless use of dangling modifiers

A potential danger in drafting legislation is that modifiers (adjectival and adverbial words, phrases and clauses) are left ‘dangling’, so that it is unclear to which word or set of words they attach. Extreme care needs to be taken to ensure that this does not happen:

The Board may make annual grants to persons from its general fund or from any of its other funds with the approval of the Minister.

The underlined adverbial phrase dangles because it is possible to read the underlined words either as modifying only grants from ‘other funds’ or

as modifying ‘general fund’ as well. This can be clarified by correct use of punctuation, or by changing the word order, or both. Thus:

The Board may make annual grants to persons from its general fund or, with the approval of the Minister, from any of its other funds.

or, depending on the policy:

The Board may, with the approval of the Minister, make annual grants to persons from its general fund or from any of its other funds.

Where a dangling modifier appears in the middle of a sentence and is capable of applying equally to words or groups of words which precede or follow, it is said to ‘squint’. Thus:

The Commissioner may order an importer within seven days of importation of the goods to file an affidavit stating…

It is not clear whether the underlined adverbial phrase modifies ‘may order’ or ‘file an affidavit’. Again, the ambiguity is avoided by punctuating correctly and placing the underlined phrase in the correct position in the sentence:

The Commissioner may, within seven days of importation of the goods, order an importer to file an affidavit stating…

or, depending on the policy:

The Commissioner may order an importer to file, within seven days of importation of goods, an affidavit stating…

6.4.6 Excessive use of cross-referencing

Reliance on other provisions, in the same or other legislation, while it has a limited place in legislation, often calls for searching in other pieces of legislation that may not be available to the user, and sometimes (e.g. where mutatis mutandis or a similar expression is used) for statutory construction of the other provisions.

Subject to the provisions of the Evidence Act, and to any rules made under section 356(1)(f) of this Act, the record of a confession made in accordance with this section is admissible in evidence against the person who made it.

In this Act “bank” has the meaning given in Part II of the Banking Act, and “financial institution” has the meaning given by section 3 of the Financial Institutions Act.

“interest in a share” is to be construed as provided under section 225(2) to (10) of the Companies Act, read with the following modifications:

the substitution of “including” for “otherwise than” in subsection (6)(d); and
the deletion of subsection (9)(b).

6.5 The aims of plain English in legislation

To limit the ideas expressed in a legislative sentence
Not to allow sentences to get too long so as to interfere with communication of the central message of the provision
Where necessary, to break up the format of sentences into paragraphs (see Chapter 7)
To follow the standard usage and styles of modern English
To use words in common use rather than elaborate or obscure ones (see the lists below)
To eliminate unnecessary words and expressions
To avoid cumbersome and unnecessary words of reference or emphasis
To avoid archaic words and expressions
To avoid Latin and French words or expressions as far as possible (see the lists below)
To use the active rather than the passive form as a general rule
To avoid dangling modifiers
As far as possible, to limit the use of cross-referencing to other parts of the legislation and, even more so, to other legislation.

6.6 Words and phrases to avoid or use with care

Archaic words to avoid or replace | Replace with
aforesaid, said | the, that
hereby | [omit]
hereinafter/before | in section(s)… etc.
lessee | tenant
lessor | landlord
provided that | but, however
servant | employee
such (pronoun: ‘if such was the case’) | it, that, they
thereafter (-in, -under, etc.) | after (in, under) it
thereupon | then
the same (pronoun: ‘if the same has been declared unfit…’) | it, they

Words and phrases to avoid or use sparingly | Corresponding words to be preferred
as a consequence of | because of
by means of | by
by virtue of | by, under
despite the fact that | although
endeavour | try
expiration of | end of, expiry of
for the purpose of | to
in accordance with | as, under
in pursuance of | as, under
in relation to | about, concerning
in the event that | if
notwithstanding | despite
prior to | before
purchase | buy
subsequent to | after
such (adjective: ‘such persons who…’) | the, that, those
until such time as | until
with a view to | to
with reference to | about, concerning
with regard to | about, concerning
with respect to | on, about
Pairs of words meaning the same thing |
due and payable | due, payable
fit and proper | fit, suitable
just and equitable | just, equitable, reasonable, fair
null and void | void, of no effect
save and except | except, unless
unless and until | unless, until
Latin phrases to avoid or use sparingly | English equivalents [or literal translations]
ab initio | from the outset, …beginning
ad valorem | related to the value
bona fide | in good faith
de facto/jure | in fact/law
de novo | again, re-…
doli incapax | incapable of (committing) crime
ex parte | without notice to the other party
in camera | in closed court
in extremis | on the point of death
in loco parentis | in place of a parent
in pari materia | analogous with
inter alia | among(st) other things
inter alios | among(st) other persons
mutatis mutandis | with the necessary changes
per se | in itself
pro rata | proportionately
sine die | with no fixed date, indefinitely
sui generis | of its own kind, in its own category
sui juris | under no legal disability
But note that the following Latin expressions have gained common acceptance as technical legal ones that do not easily translate into a convenient plain English equivalent
certiorari | [to be more carefully informed]
ex gratia | as a matter of favour, without legal obligation
ex officio | by virtue of appointment/post/office
habeas corpus | [you have the body]
intra/ultra vires | [within/beyond the powers]
mandamus | [we command]
mens rea | [guilty mind]
nolle prosequi | [unwilling to prosecute]
post mortem | [after death]
prima facie | [at first glance]
pro forma | [for form’s sake]